<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-27T19:26:51+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ludwig Winkler</title><subtitle>Jekyll version of the Massively theme by HTML5UP</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Money Laundering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/moneylaundering/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money Laundering" /><published>2022-11-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/moneylaundering</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/moneylaundering/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-should-you-put-your-bills-in-the-laundry-machine&quot;&gt;Why should you put your bills in the laundry machine?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the spread of Covid-19 has made us all very sensitive to germs and viruses.
Cash changes hand a lot of times and thus is the perfect medium to transmit diseases.
… yeah, I’m actually talking about the art of financial subterfuge obscuring the illicit origin of illegally obtained money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from their ideologically motivated peers, criminals are driven by one thing: profit. 
Greed is the principal goal, but people that require money laundering skills don’t sell stolen chewing gum on the school yard.
Instead, they have millions or even billions originating from illegal sources which need to be moved into accessible bank accounts of the criminals.
Thus the money needs to be able to be handled just like any other legitimate money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is, as soon as a sovereign (and hopefully clean) police force would ascertain that an investment was done with money originating from illicit sources, they are most of the time allowed to seize the investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is now to disguise the financial assets so they can be used without detection of the illegal activity that produced them. 
The term ‘money laundering’ describes the process of transforming the monetary proceeds derived from criminal activity into funds of an apparently legal origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who is a potential user of money laundering? 
Drug cartels, terrorists, mobsters or the mafia, human traffickers, illegal arms dealers and the list goes on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money-laundering-methods&quot;&gt;Money Laundering Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principal, money laundering consists of three distinct stages: placement, layering, and integration.
Personally, I use the terms entry, obfuscation, and integration which are more vivid terms in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to place the money at the entrance points of the modern financial system.
If you got cash, you get ‘smurfs’ which repeatedly deposit money amounts just below the reporting line.
Usually, deposits below 10.000 USD don’t have to be reported in the US, which led to bank tellers close to the Mexican border on the US side receiving up to 400.000 USD of deposits per week in cartel-linked accounts parceled out in 10k portions and brought by local Americans to reduce suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step is to obfuscate the origin of the cash.
You start moving money through different accounts or start to create round-about invoices with complicit companies.
For example, a smurf would deposit money in a bank account or would pay a bogus invoice for a company that only exists on paper.
Then the fake company would pay a fake invoice of another company which would then have an apparently legitimate income stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Layering or obfuscation serves the purpose of creating a fake, seemingly legitimate origin of the funds.
Once a fake story for the money has been created, the main financial investments can be accomplished.
Imagine a suspicious person trying to buy a condominium in New York with a pile of unexplained cash and a real estate company headquartered in the Bahamas buying the apartment next to him.
The real estate company got its capital from the drug trade, human trafficking or sanction-busting arms trade just like the individual next door, but the police would be way more interested in the sole person with 15 million USD in unexplained cash and an unexplained stream of income.
The real estate company first laundered its capital through multiple layers of obfuscation and wouldn’t provide a reasonable doubt for the origin of its money.
It’s basically all about appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll outline some of the more common money laundering schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have fake trials in which both parties are in on the jig and one party pays reimbursement to create a fake story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exaggerated or even fake invoices which can include non-existent services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively Mr. Criminal can buy real estate way below the market value with the difference to the full price being paid in illegal cash. 
Afterwards, the property is quickly sold for the appropriate price on the open market.
The cash is illegal and is given to the original owner and the money launderer creates a bogus profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can convert illegal cash to casino jetons and a little bit is used for gambling.
Since gambling is intrinsically stochastic nobody can really trace back when you lost or when you won more money.
After some time, the casino jetons are cashed back in and you get a receipt that you’re apparently an awesome gambler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most straightforward method is still fictitious business activity of cash-based enterprises.
There, the illegal cash is simply mixed into the income stream proportional to the untainted money stream.
I mean proportional since even the most amazing taco truck usually doesn’t make 200 million USD in revenue per year.
The usual suspects are dry cleaning shops, casinos, supermarkets, drug stores, car shops, and anything that has a largely cash-based income stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auctions of hard-to-value objects have also become a popular method and especially the art market has been captured.
You basically let two fake personas outbid each other with your own illegal cash.
The object with little intrinsic value is offered by you and the bidders get your illegal cash.
The sale creates a fake yet clean receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;offshore-jurisdictions-and-banking&quot;&gt;Offshore Jurisdictions and Banking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal safeguard against money laundering is the stringent enforcement of Know-Your-Customer (KYC) laws.
Ideally, the entry points to the financial system should have gatekeepers who check for potentially illegal sources of money.
Obviously, there is a conflict of interest since a lot of money means a lot of business for banks a similar institutions as was shown by HSBC scandal with the cartel money or the Raul Salinas story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, a whole industry sector has blossomed between the beaches of the Caribbean, the mountains of the Alps, and in general small insignificant countries selling the legislative sovereignty to the highest bidder: the offshore finance industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offshore finance centers implement effectively no regulation of the financial industry within their borders and often similarly implement convenient financial secrecy laws by allowing trusts, straight-out banking secrecy limiting the information of who actually owns a bank account, nominee directors of shell companies hiding the true owner of a company and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using the intricacy of modern tax codes, you can create a multitude of opaque companies which move money between them for no apparent reason.
For law enforcement, proving that the money being moved around is originally from illicit conduct is close to impossible.
Since innocence until proven wrong is a tenet in well-functioning judicial systems, it becomes close to impossible to prove the illegal source of the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using international banking, one could use mirror trades like the ones Deutsche Bank executed for Russian customers in 2007.
Two well-capitalized accounts, one in London and one in Moscow, would be under the control of the same entity at Deutsche Bank.
The Moscow based account would use dirty money to buy stocks in a company and Deutsche Bank holds the stocks as a broker.
Via ‘remote booking’ the Moscow front office would then conduct a sale of the same stocks in the London market place for an apparently unaffiliated entity in London obtaining euros or dollars in that brokerage account.
The money to buy the stocks in London in the first place can be obtained via loans in Russia for example.
But since the London entity was controlled by the same person, they spend Roubles in Moscow and obtained and an equal amount of Dollars in a financial offshore jurisdiction.
The sale of the stocks in London created a squeaky-clean bill of financial health for the Dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can also buy options in the derivative market for which you pay a premium.
These options have intrinsic value and can be sold, such that the dirty money can be used for the premium payments and the option itself can be sold for a higher value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you could use looped swap contracts across borders.
Interest rate swaps make one party pay the London Interbank Offered Rate (the LIBOR, itself subject to major manipulations at the cost of millions of people as portrayed in ‘The Spider Network’ by David Enrich) while the other party pays a fixed rate and thus they ‘swap’ interest rates.
If you now chain these swaps in a circle, you can easily move money with a valid, seemingly clean contract from Moscow to London and then to Moscow back again.
Of course, the round-tripping is not obfuscated but each party seemingly gets a clean origin of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the money has been safely moved into offshore financial centers it can then be used to invest.
The irony of many international active criminals is that they move their wealth out of their often unstable countries and park it in luxury real estate in London, Paris, and New York.
There has been a rise in super tall skyscrapers in New York City which is commonly referred to as ‘Billionaires Row’.
But while these apartments offer amazing views of the City high above the problems of ordinary people, the ownership is more than opaque.
A majority of the luxury real estate is bought by shell companies and they are often occupied only a couple of days of the year.
Their main purpose is that since they were legitimately bought, and the front companies in secrecy jurisdictions buying them being nearly impossible to crack open, it is next to impossible to prove that they had been bought with money obtained through illegal means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially in the case of the US, there is an interesting historical anecdote to tell.
Before 9/11, not a lot of people were interested in anti-money-laundering (AML) legislation.
But once the terrorist attacks occurred, everybody suddenly got super interested in how it was possible that a terrorist organization was able to pay for the flight school in the US of the terrorist that hijacked the planes and steered them into their targets.
It’s not exactly that Al-Qaida was selling hot dogs in front of the Metropolitan Museum in Central Park.
Thus stringent anti-money-laundering laws were passed targeting every possible nook and cranny in which illegal money could be parked.
Included were luxury real estate and luxury products such that prior to a transaction in these industries Know-Your-Customer (KYC) procedures and other AML laws had to be conducted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a short while later, precisely these luxury industries were exempt from KYC and AML procedures.
Lawmakers were lobbied by the industries to exempt them such that they could continue to sell luxury real estate and products to customers they knew little about.
To be fair, at a certain wealth you might want peace of mind and privacy and not see your latest purchase plastered over the morning edition of a tabloid.
Nevertheless, it is a peculiar coincidence precisely because luxury items give you the ability to store large amounts of money in a small number of objects.
Semi-fancy art paintings for 25 Million USD in an auction, a super expensive apartment in the UK or a gold-plated Lamborghini, none of these transactions require a stringent KYC procedure now anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reputation-laundering&quot;&gt;Reputation Laundering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do you do after you’ve laundered all your money?
Essentially you have a criminal or a criminally connected person with large amounts of cash.
After you laundered your money, it’s now time to launder your reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of this is the story of Dmitry Firtash.
In essence, Dmytro Firtash is just a puppet for Semion Mogilevich, the mastermind of the Russian mob.
He came out of nowhere and was suddenly made co-owner of RosUkrEnergo, which is an intermediary that for some unknown reason gets to buy gas cheaply from Gazprom and sell expensively to Europe.
Since Gazprom is solidly in the hand of the Kremlin, it is assumed that these intermediary organizations pocket the difference and transfer it to Putin’s kleptocracy.
Dmitry Firtash came out of nowhere within a position nobody could really explain resulting in money that is a bit shady, to say the least.
Nevertheless, he quickly ingratiated himself with the who is who in the UK’s public sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went through all the necessary procedures that I will outline down below to become one of London’s elite and seemingly respected members.
The first step was to obviously buy expensive real estate which gives ample room to host dinners and invite important people.
This lets you put roots down and people consider you a member of London’s exclusive super-rich social circle.
Next, you hire a public relations firm ( in itself a more than a weird concept) that will manage your public image.
They will put you in touch with members of parliament and other prestigious people which will serve as directors for you charity or foundation which you obviously founded only for the reason to pay prestigious people.
The charity, foundation or whatever should be nice and uncontroversial when people think of it: be socially active, give out stipends, build sports facilities or anything that gives you a nice PR photo op.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that you have paid a company to give you a good image with a suitable background, the PR firm will continue to actively forge new relationships.
You host dinners with ex-politicians with a powerful rolodex, you cast your dubious conglomerate as a useful and relevant aid to the national interests of the country.
Commodities, energy, media, and construction are of interest to a country but are hardly irreplaceable.
Nevertheless, you are now a useful member of society and worth keeping in the fold.
Another step is to be philanthropic in high society circles by sponsoring new buildings for colleges, preferably Oxford, Cambridge, and the London colleges like UCL.
Dmitry Firtash founded a Ukrainian studies program that brought him in close contact with exclusive circles of Oxbridge.
Given that London’s elite is definitely to almost exclusively educated at Oxbridge that brings you in fortuitous contact with a little of influential people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first aim of these PR shenanigans is to make the client too well-connected and too important to discard.
The second part of reputation laundering in the UK is to use its potent libel laws to make reporting on the source of these people’s wealth impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;libel-law--tourism&quot;&gt;Libel Law &amp;amp; Tourism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultra-wealthy people don’t just travel to the UK to park their money there but also like to travel there to suffocate any reporting on their dodgy wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English law allows them to sue for libel for any published statements which are allegedly defaming a named or identifiable individual if these have caused a loss in their trade or profession or just plainly damage their reputation.
This is pretty standard around the world and is present in almost any judicial code.
What sets the UK apart is that in a libel case, the allegedly defamatory statement is presumed to be false unless the defendant can prove its veracity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has conferred the status of ‘most favored nation’ (to borrow a WTO term) onto the UK from ultra-high net worth people with questionable sources of income.
In essence, the burden of proof lies with the defendant such that even the slightest insinuation is impossible unless is airtight and reinforced with proof.
Any sentence like ‘ … who has reportedly close dealings with the Russian mob …’ could set loose the legal hounds upon the publication outfit under which auspice this sentence was printed.
Just imagine a multi-billionaire going to court against an investigative newspaper with the billionaire plaintiff being able to bankrupt the investigative newspaper through legal costs alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of this is the excellently written book ‘Putin’s Kleptocracy - Who owns Russia’ by Karen Dawisha which was essentially shunned by every publisher in the UK for fear of being bankrupted by legal proceedings and ultimately had to be published in the US.
The rebellious colony across the Atlantic had passed the SPEECH Act of 2010 which made foreign libel judgements without equivalent free speech enforcements unenforcible in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To top it out, a public official or public figure as a plaintiff has to prove actual malice in writing possible ‘slander’ causing professional or reputational harm.
A private individual instead must only prove negligence to be able to win the libel case.
Especially in the case of off-shore finance and other dealings taking place in the dark, nothing is ever fully known and the slightest mistake which can be exploited by the plaintiff as negligence can lead to bankrupting the entire publishing outfit or journalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misuse of libel lawsuits become so egregious that the libel law slightly reformed in 2013.
While it made winning libel cases harder for plaintiffs as they now had to prove actual and objective harm, it left the legal costs unchanged.
Simply maintaining a legal team which can hold its own against high-powered legal advice from oligarchs would bankrupt the defendant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this is not limited to news papers.
Even the National Crime Agency, the UK’s main police force for economic crime and organized crime, is capped by litigious oligarchs.
In a more than questionable legal setup the NCA is required to pay the full legal fees in case of a loss in court of the defendant.
Given that shady ultra-high net worth people are financially able to employ law firms of the likes of Mishcon de Reya, the legal fees quickly become too much to bear by the public office.
Thus the effect is that the economic crime division of the UK is legally hamstrung to prosecute shady billionaires afraid it will loose its entire annual budget to a single criminal case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual budget of the NCA is around 4.3 million pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oligarchs buy third houses in Kensington and Mayfair for 80 million pounds …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">Greenbacks, Soap and Hopefully No Questions</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kleptocracy alongside Vodka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracyrussia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kleptocracy alongside Vodka" /><published>2022-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracyrussia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracyrussia/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;kleptocracy-in-russia&quot;&gt;Kleptocracy in Russia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian kleptocratic system is more straight forward and relies more on direct theft than currency manipulation.
But here, too, we have to first go back in time a bit to 1980’s in the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-bit-of-historical-context&quot;&gt;A Bit of Historical Context&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposedly everybody is familiar with ‘Star Was’, the saga of one messed up family that keeps an entire galaxy busy with its family issues.
It’s so popular that Mickey Mouse eventually decided to to buy up the IP to milk it harder than an Irish cow (which has a better life than the Disneyland employees).
Ronald Reagan, being an actor originally who read the likes of Hayek and Friedman on between shoots while on set, pushed ahead with a ‘Star Wars’ missile defense program which would protect the US from Russian ballistic missiles.
It was the final chapter of a tremendous arms race which had pitted the US and the Soviet Union against each other in the search for ever more advanced weapons.
While eventually being massively overhyped, it did let the Russians realize that they could not win the arms race with their inefficient planned economy.
After a bit more than half a century of planning their economies during which the Soviet Union had been able to pull of tremendous feats of engineering by concentrating labour, resources and a disregard for human necessities, the realization set in among the higher ups in the Soviet economy that they could not sustain the arms race on their own terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even during the darkest economic days of the Soviet Union, there had been a multitude of black market operations who provided the population with a few basic goods.
These operations were mainly run by mostly ethnic outsiders such as Chechens, Jews and Kazakhs.
Due to latent, political and sometimes rampant anti-semitism, Jews often had to struggle to survive in country in which the word ‘progrom’ had been gained its infamous meaning.
Then criminal enterprises in a country which deemed criminality a capitalist disease and thus couldn’t exist in the communist union became a very attractive alternative occupation.
Even nowadays it remains interesting high the percentage of Jewish gangsters is in the criminal scene of Russia given its overall percentage such as Semion Mogilevich (long time on the FBI’s most wanted list), Marat Balagula or Evsei Agron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KGB as the most powerful security organization was tasked with controlling the black market but quickly realized that they could run their own protection rackets and make money out of the economic misery of their compatriots.
To some extent, the existence of the black market was even timidly encouraged as it eased some of the economic hard ship by increasing the supply, even at inflated prices.
This led to a political-security-criminal nexus in which KGB officers were quick to learn their first lessons in private enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in the 1980’s a motley crew of KGB officers and Russian economists began to think about a new hybrid system which could have developed similarly to the Chinese emergence out of communism into hybrid, controlled capitalism.
During the Glasnost &amp;amp; Perestroika period, Gorbachev became loosening the iron grip on the Soviet Unions political and economic system and urged other Warsaw Pact countries to follow suit.
In 1991, the New Union Treaty was signed due to incessant and increasing unrest of the other Soviet republics which handed more control and independence from Moscow to the individual republics.
Hardliners in the Soviet Unions Communist Party wanted to have none of that and staged a coup on August 19-22 1991.
While the KGB detained Gorbachev at his holiday estate on the Black Sea, they did not arrest Boris Yeltsin who was able to confront the putschists and effectively ended it.
In the wake of the coup the Communist Party of the Soviet Union was effectively dissolved by Yeltsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-looting-begins&quot;&gt;The Looting Begins&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The East German Stasi had a dedicated department called ‘Kommerzielle Koordinierung’ for stealing western military and dual use technology as well as procure foreign currency reserves through smuggling.
It is estimated that up to 50% of all Soviet weapons systems at the end of the cold war were based upon stolen blue prints from the West.
But the technological gap became so wide, that the Soviets weren’t able to implement the blue prints anymore as the manufacturing capabilities were ultimately lagging far behind.
Initially it was organized under infamous Markus Wolf’s espionage department before coming a force of itself, a sign of how important it became to East Germany and in extension to the Soviet Union.
The KGB had developed a similar department for economic and financial logistics in foreign countries.
A multitude of shell companies and banks had been founded and were controlled by the First Main Directorate if the KGB in charge of foreign intelligence.
These shell companies were used to buy resources and material on the international markets as well as transfer money out of the country to causes which were deemed important to the Soviet Union or the KGB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More often than not though, the profits from the difference between Soviet and market prices were stashed away in the untold bank accounts and companies, control over which was held by the KGB.
The funneling of black cash was done through ‘friendly firms’ which were shell companies or corrupted real companies through which untraceable money went on its way to its final use.
These were front companies serving just as financial conduits to which other companies wishing to do business in or with the Soviet Union had to pay money for bogus or inflated prices.
These ‘friendly firms’ could then disburse their enormous profits to fund for example the communist parties in Spain, the UK and France.
Sometimes they were busy with smuggling technology to the Soviet Union or East Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were ‘friendly banks’ in which the profits of barter deals was stashed.
Often, these ‘friendly firms’ would buy natural resources, which the Soviet Union had a lot of, at extremely undervalued Soviet Prices and sold them on the world market for the spot price.
Later during Putin’s reign as trade chief under Anatoly Sobchack in St. Petersburg, a license was given out to export 13 tons of rare earth metals for 1/2000 th of the current world market price.
The profit margin is directly there in the divisor and the part of the profits of such export deals were then stashed in accounts in ‘friendly banks’ such as Switzerland’s Banco del Gottardo or secrecy jurisdictions like Panama, Hong Kong or the British Channel Islands.
The sums could then be used as slush funds for communist party to destabilize the West or do whatever else they wanted to achieve, but more importantly, they were overseen by the KGB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Gorbachev’s reform sent the Soviet Union towards unruly chaos, his deputy signed off the intention in August of 1990 to create an ‘invisible economy’ managed by ‘trusted custodians’ with a network of shell companies to spirit away the wealth of the Communist Party.
When the Communist Party was dissolved on live TV by Boris Yeltsin on August 25 1991, this automatically raised the question what would happen to all the money, foreign currencies, property and investments nominally under their control.
Less than three day after Yeltsin had averted the coup in Moscow with a fiery speech on a tank, Nikolay Kruchina, the Parties property department chief, fell out of his window.
A month later, his predecessor Georgy Pavlov fell out of his window as well at the age of 81.
Eleven days Dmitry Lissovolik, the American Section chief of Communist Party’s International Department, which oversaw funding of international operations and was thus at the heart of the web of shell companies, fell to his death as well.
All three men had deep insights into the property of the Communist Party which was officially valued at 9 billion USD but unofficially valued at many times over that.
Thus when the new government came looking for the money that the Communist Party had amassed over the last 80 years, they found nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second round of lopsided privatization occurred with the creation of cooperatives, the Soviet version of private enterprises first allowed in 1987, inside large state-owned enterprises which started selling off the huge stockpiles of strategic reservers.
The directors started privatizing the state-owned enterprises from the inside out by controlling the cash flow in the large, still state-owned, enterprises.
Back then, having a positive cash flow allowed you to achieve extraordinary gains in a massively inefficient organize economy.
The government agreed to privatize parts of the Russian economy via a voucher system during a time of rampant hyper inflation when the general population had little nerve for long-term investing.
Additionally, the vast majority of the population were unaccustomed to the idea of investing and owning shares after 80 years of communism.
Since people were more interested in surviving, the company directors, the Russian mafia and other insiders with access to the cash flow were able to buy up large amounts of the share vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small addition to the cooperative legislation allowed the creation of banks which is where the real massive privatization of the Russian economy started.
Among the first banks to obtain a foreign currency trading permission was the Menatep bank of Mikhail Khodorkovsky.
CIA station chief Richard Palmer and Procurator General Aristov claim that between 500 Miollion to 1.5 Billion USD of vanished Communist party funds were used by ex-KGB officers to fund these first commercial banks and at the same time hide the money.
Among other schemes, they used the official state exchange rate of 1 USD to 65 kopecks to change roubles into US dollars and buy private computers in the West.
They then sold the computers in Russia with the value being close to 40 roubles for each dollar of import computers.
You can probably see how you can print exponential money by using currency exchange arbitrage and cycling the roubles back through the official state sanctioned exchange rate into dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third theft from the Russian people after the billions of CPSU money and the mismanaged voucher system was committed during the privatization of the hugely profitable sectors of the formerly Russian state economy creating the first generation of Russian oligarchs.
The transition of 80 years of planned economy mired in inefficiency, political suppression and corruption towards a free market went as smoothly as one would think.
The government under Boris Yeltsin soon fell on fiscally hard times and was in dire need for cash to keep the country running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original sin of the Russian market economy was the loans-for-shares program, also termed the second wave of privatization.
For reasons unknown or inconvenient at the moment, Boris Yeltsin’s government refrained from creating its own treasury and instead simply deposited the governments funds into the oligarchs privately owned banks.
Without doing any work, they could suddenly invest money worth an entire countries budget into high yielding investements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Boris Berezovsky put it somewhat humorously upon being asked whether he would let his wealths provenance be checked: ‘Absolutely, I would submit all my wealth to legal scrutiny. Except for the first million.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the government was still cash-strapped and needed money fast.
The banks agreed to give the government private loans and as collateral took considerable minority stakes in large state-owned enterprises predominantly in the natural resources sector.
When the government couldn’t repay the loans, they were allowed to auction off their stakes and pocket the proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeltsin held the oligarchs politically hostage by receiving the loans before the election but ensuring the auction to sell them off would only occur after the election.
Thus the oligarchs had a massive interest in ensuring Yeltsin reelection.
To little surprise, the government couldn’t in fact repay the loans and the oligarchs through their political clout were able to rig the auctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus Potanin got Norilsk Nickel, the worlds largest nickel and platinum producer, with 1.2 billion USD of profits in 1995 for a mere 175 million USD in the same year.
Khodorkovsky took control of 78 percent of Yukos valued at 5 billion USD for 310 million USD.
Berezovsky took over Sibneft worth around 3 billion USD for just 100 million USD.
After the auctions, Boris Berezovsky remarked that seven bankers now controlled 50 percent of the Russian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KGB and the company directors tried to fight the take over but were only able to win two out of the numerous auctions.
During one auction, the company directors closed down the closest airport and armed guards blocked the streets to prevent anybody but the company directors to bid in the auction.
It was truly the ‘Wild, Wild East’.
Yet, while many of the first generation of oligarchs had been nurtured by the KGB itself, the securocrats quickly found themselves outwitted and outmaneuvered by the freshly minted billionaires.
For an organization steeped in the sense of control over an entire country, this was a moment which was neither forgiven nor forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grudges and resentment created during that privatization in which the KGB lost economic control of the country created the vengeance with which the Putin government went after the first generation of oligarchs.
It led to the rise of the ‘siloviki’, ex-security and military personnel, which installed Vladimir Putin in power and viciously took over the country by expropriating the oligarchs or pummeling them into political submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-1999-legislative-and-2000-presidential-election&quot;&gt;The 1999 Legislative and 2000 Presidential Election&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian constitution officially allows only two terms which Boris Yeltsin had served after his reelection in 1996.
But there was a minor issue at hand for the Yeltsin family: there was massive resistance to his corruption and multiple investigations into his and his family’s dealings during his presidency.
The ‘Family’ as it was called consisted of the Yeltsin family as well as close friends who had used the power position to enrich themselves.
The problem was that the most probably succesor to Yeltsin was Yevgeny Primakov who had clearly signalled to clear up and prosecute the graft of Yeltsins inner circle.
He teamed with popular Moscow mayor Yury Luzhkov and gouvernors of the Russian Federation’s provinces to position himself as the clear winner of the 1999 election.
Since Yeltsin himself couldn’t run anymore they needed a viable succesor who could prevent Primakov’s wrath and grant them immediate immunity from any legal prosecutions once he and his family and cronies left the presidency.
So they settled on Vladimir Putin and Boris Yeltsin dissolved his government to force reelections which was hopefully too soon for the opposition to organize a viable campaign.
In August of 1999, he made Putin his prime minister.
But yet again there was one problem: Yeltsin’s approval rating were at a rock-bottom 2% and hardly anyone in the population knew Putin at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of Yeltsin first presidency was overshadowed by the first Chechen War, in which between 30.000 to 100.000 Chechen civilians were killed.
There is a haunting transcript from a radio communication between two officers who had fought side by side in Afghanistan and now faced each other during the Battle of Grozny.
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NnA552tMV8g&quot;&gt;link to the video and transcript&lt;/a&gt; can be found on YouTube and tells a story of senseless murder between friends condensed in less than a minute.
The date in the title of the video is wrong as the Battle of Grozny was waged during the First Chechen War in 1994-1996 and not the second, which was in 1999 to 2009.
The Russian army demolished Grozny with artillery fire after failed first attempts to take the city in what was described as the largest destruction of a civilian city since Stalingrad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless the first Chechen War created a menacing enemy for the Russian Federation.
Then suddenly bombs started to go off in appartment buildings in September of 1999 killing close to 300 civilians sleeping in their beds in Moscow and Volgodonsk.
While it was initially believed to be the work of Chechen terrorist, the Duma speaker Gennady Seleznyov made an announcement that a bomb had exploded in Volgodonsk on 13 September 1999.
Nobody took him for full until a bomb did explode three days later on 16 September.
This was the first suspicious incident which was quickly overshadowed by the prevented bombing of an appartment complex in Ryazan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the evening of 22 September 1999, a resident saw two shady men carry sacks of what appeared to be sugar into the basement of an appartment building.
The car was from Moscow but the license plate was altered to make appear local.
After multiple bombings in the same month, the resident was suspicious and alerted the police which found three sacks of white powder totalling 150kg with a timer set to 5.30 the next day.
The local bomb squad identified the white powder as RDX, a military grade explosive which is not especially easy to organize.
Terrorists commonly use ammonium nitrate which can be produced with supplies from the local hardware/gardening store as it also used as a fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the next day a telephone service employee listened in on a suspicious phone call which was traced back to three FSB officers who were apprehended by the local police.
Prior to the identification of these three security officers, both the local FSB and the headquarters had been on the same page that the averted bombing had been the work of terrorists.
But as soon as the three FSB officers from Moscow had been identified, the FSB director Nikolay Patrushev suddenly made it a training exercise to which the local Ryazan FSB denounced vehemently.
The RDX suddenly became sugar according to the FSB director and the two privates in Ryzan who had tried to use the RDX/sugar as sweetener during their shift and found it to taste terribly were reprimanded by the FSB personally to ‘forget everything’ and ‘not get mixed up in such troubles’ after telling their story to an investigative newspaper.
Additionally, all investigations were hindered by the FSB and even the Duma member Trepashkin was suddenly arrested when he started asking uncomfortable questions regarding the Chechen origins of the perpetrators.
The Duma even voted to seal all documents on the Ryazan bombing for the next 75 years and officially forbade any investigations into the FSB’s role in the bombing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there has been no investigation there is nothing that can be said with certainty.
But the bombings and the final botched bombing does become malicious and cynical once the meteoric rise of Vladimir Putins approval ratings is taken into account.
As a tough talking KGB guy who ran a campaign on order and restraining the chaos of the Yeltsin time, the bombings came to a fortuitous time as it gave a perfect pretense to exalt his strengths as a tough policing guy.
The bombings played greatly into his approval ratings going from a mere 2% to 45% right before the presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last note on the legitimacy of the 2000 presidential election on 26 March 2000:
It was reported that the region of Chechnya, an astonishing 50.63% voted for Putin.
This result was apparently achieved after the Russian military had laid siege to Grozny from December 1999 to February 2000.
Apparently the half the population of a bombed out region with 30.000-100.000 civilian casualties from a war a mere 4 years ago voted for a guy who said he would march back into Chechnya to finish what was started in the first Chechen war.
I guess elections are full of suprises …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;russian-kleptocracy-today&quot;&gt;Russian Kleptocracy Today&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corruption in Russia has taken on such extremes that the Moscow station chief of the CIA Richard Palmer summarized the extents of the system in 1999 as following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”
For the U.S. to be like Russia is today, it would be necessary to have massive corruption by the majority of the members of Congress as well as by the Departments of Justice and Treasury, and agents of the FBI, CIA, DIA (Defense Intelligence Agency), IRS, Marshal Ser-vice, Border Patrol, state and local police officers, the Federal Reserve Bank, Supreme Court justices, U.S. District court judges, support of the varied Organized Crime families, the leadership of the Fortune 500 companies, at least half of the banks in the U.S., and the New York Stock Exchange. This cabal would then have to seize the gold at Fort Knox and the federal assets deposited in the entire banking system. It would have to take control of the key industries such as oil, natural gas, mining, precious and semi-precious metals, forestry, cotton, construction, insurance, and banking industries and then claim these items to be their private property. The legal system would have to nullify most of the key provisions against corruption, conflict of interest, criminal conspiracy, money laundering, economic fraud and weaken tax evasion laws. This unholy alliance would then have to spend about 50% of its billions in profits to bribe officials that remained in government and be the primary supporters of all of the political candidates. Then, most of the stolen funds, excess profits and bribes would have to be sent to off-shore banks for safekeep-ing. Finally, while claiming that the country was literally bankrupt and needed vast infusions of foreign aid to survive, this conspiratorial group would invest billions in spreading illegal activities to developed foreign countries. … The President would not only be aware of all these activities but would support them.
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary I read in Karen Dawishas excellent book ‘Putin’s Kleptocracy’ perfectly summarizes the current system and I’m just going to quote it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”
It became clear to Russian and Western observers long before Putin started his third full term as president in 2012 that he operated a complex informal system in which subgroups were constantly balanced against each other, with Putin alone as the ultimate arbiter.
His power derived less from the institutional legitimacy conferred by being head of state than from the successful operation of a tribute system that obliged all participants to recognize his authority.
In the words of American economists Clifford Gaddy from the Brookings Institution and Barry Ickes from Pennsylvania State University, Putin operates a “protection racket” dependent on a code of behavior that severely punishes disloyalty while allowing access to economic predation on a world-historic scale for the inner core of his elite.
By his third term, he had created a highly controlled security system able to use the laws, the media, and the security forces as a means of intimidating, and critically balancing, rival economic elites.
Others have called it a “corporation” “Kremlin, Inc.,” “a sistema,” or a “corporatist-kleptocratic regime.
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, billionaires in the wide world own 1-2% of a countries wealth.
In Russia, this number is turned upside down as 110 billionairs own 35% of Russias wealth.
Furthermore, the amount of capital flight is so extreme, that 50% of all Russian wealth is reported to reside outside of Russia.
Now this also points the finger indirectly squarely at the West, especially the US and the UK, in which huge sums of Russian money is invested in luxury real estate and miscellaneous luxury items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judicial system is so steady in the grip of the kleptocracy that hundred of thousands of entrepreneurs are currently incarcerated in Russian prisons.
They have been framed by competitors or just plain black mail racketeers who bribed the criminal system with police and judges.
While the average salary has grown to 1650 USD per year, the median salary remains stagnant at 871 USD, even below Indias median salary of 1040 USD.
This gap is explained with the extreme inequality relating to billionaires and millionaires who work hand in glove with the kleptocracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A worrying trend is that 35% of workers under 30 have a government job which is paid for by extractive industries such as timber, oil, gas and minerals.
This is the result of a fusion of a resource curse combined with a kleptocracy in which nobody is interested in building impartial institutions which serve the public and not a well connected kleptomaniac.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">What was ours is now mine, ex-comrade</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kleptocracy, Lebanese Style</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracylebanon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kleptocracy, Lebanese Style" /><published>2022-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracylebanon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/kleptocracylebanon/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;kleptocracy-in-lebanon&quot;&gt;Kleptocracy in Lebanon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-bit-of-context-which-is-a-wild-ride-in-itself&quot;&gt;A bit of context which is a wild ride in itself&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern story of the Lebanon starts with a French Monsieur Francois Georges-Picot, a British Gentleman Mark Sykes and the Ottoman Sultan Mehmed V.
As members of the Triple Entente between France, England and Russia, the British and French had plans for the Middle East which they wanted to wrest from the control of the Ottoman Empire which had allied itself with the German Empire.
Even before the war was over, the two diplomats Picot and Sykes duked it out and divided the central Middle East into spheres of influence between France and Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British would control a strip of land ranging from modern Israel/Palestine through Jordan to central and southern Iraq, whereas France would control modern day Lebanon, Syria and northern Iraq.
European powers had a specific infatuation with protecting Christians outside of Europe.
The Russians had gone to war with the Ottoman empire as they wanted to style themselves as the protectors of Christians in the Ottoman Empire and Caucasus.
Similarly, the French wanted to see themselves as protectors of the significant Christian population living in the area around Mount Lebanon and in the Levant.
Important for the later story, the region was characterized by multi-ethnic and multi-religious cohabitation, with Maronite Christians, Druze, Shia and Sunni with their subdominations Alawites and Alevis also hanging around in the same region.
Maronite Christians are an Eastern Catholics while Druze are an eclectic mixture of religions and believes.
Shia and Sunni are similar to Protestants and Catholics in Christianity which split over an succession issue with the Shia’s favoring Ali, a direct descendant of the prophet Muhammed, while the Sunni favored the unrelated Abu Bakr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British and French had indirectly already come to blows during a Maronite-Druze civil war in the Levant.
While the French supported the Maronites, the British wanted to protect their interests and supported the Druze.
If you’re confused why I’m recounting Lebanon’s history on a napkin, the multi-confessional composition of Lebanon will play an important role later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the collapse of the Ottoman Empire, the French became the rulers of Lebanon under the mandate of the League of Nations.
The French would stay in Lebanon until shortly after World War 2 and the country prospered.
It was soon regarded as the Switzerland of the Middle East with a well functioning administration, a multi-lingual population and strong banking secrecy.
So literally like Switzerland, but a bit sunnier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things went well for quite some time but the ill-configured setup of the Lebanon was already discernible.
It should be noted that especially the Maronites and the Druze were ethno-religious groups which offered two ways of separating themselves from other people, through kinship and through religion.
This was unofficially encoded in the National Pact of 1943 which assigned seats and thus political power in the parliament on a 6-to-5 proportionality based on a 1932 census of the population.
Another implementation to get to grips with the multi-ethno-religious composition of the population was to predetermine the representative posts in the government according to the confession: the president was always a Maronite Christian, the speaker of the parliament a Shia and the prime minister a Sunni.
While it did not seem like the best way to govern a country, economically the strong banking sector was especially well positioned to benefit from the fresh petro money coming out of the oil rich middle eastern countries and thus the Lebanon prospered tremendously in the 1960.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-civil-war&quot;&gt;The Civil War&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right at its door step a convoluted situation had developed in the British part of the Sykes-Picot agreement.
After the establishment of the Israeli state in 1948 and the Suez War of 1956, which was also instigated by the Brits and the French over the nationalization of the Suez canal, the Israelis invaded the Sinai peninsula to open the strait of Tiran to Israeli naval vessels.
In the relatively short period of six days, Israel managed to take over the Sinai peninsula again and conquer the Gaza strip, the West Bank and East Jerusalem.
As a consequence, 300.000 Palestinians and 100.000 Syrians fled and/or were expelled from the newly occupied areas with many Palestinians fleeing to Jordan.
The suffering of the Palestinian population caused the Palestine Liberation Organization to become militarily active and soon it started accumulating large amounts of money and weapons with its headquarter established in Jordans capital Amman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PLO as the dominant recipient of political, financial and military support and prime proxy insurgency against Israel quickly became a state within the state of Jordan.
Soon, the idea was promulgated that the PLO should overthrow the Jordan Hashemite monarchy.
Obviously the Jordanian kingdom would have none of that and the short lived Jordanian civil war broke out, in which the PLO was ultimately defeated by the Jordanian armed forces in September 1970 and allowed to leave for Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fighting in September of 1970 lead to the formation of a terrorist splinter faction which called itself ‘Black September’ and which sought retribution for the expulsion from Jordan.
But they soon focused on attacking Israel again and became infamous through the massacre of Israeli athletes at the 1972 olympic games in Munich.
Unfortunately, when the PLO arrived in Lebanon the Jordanian story was repeated again as the PLO again started to behave like a semi-autonomous state within a state.
Maybe they did inspire the Hezbollah 20 years later who are behaving just the same … but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese state of political affairs had already been fragile necessitating the afore-mentioned power sharing agreements.
The sudden arrival of the PLO as the most powerful military force in Lebanon quickly pitted them against the ethno-religious militias as power had always remained with the different political factions and not with a centralized state.
Tensions started to flare up especially with the Maronite Christian Phalange militia which ultimately led to the start of the Lebanese civil war from 1975 to 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the civil war was raging, a Lebanese business man by the name of Rafic Hariri made his first millions doing construction work in Saudi-Arabia.
He quickly gained the trust of the Saudi royal family and as a native Lebanese became embroiled in the factional power plays of the Lebanese civil war.
After 15 years of civil war, the fatigued factions were ready for a peace deal and Rafic Hariri was there to broker it in one of his hotels in Ta’if in Saudi Arabia.
It was appropriately called the Ta’if agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every fight should require a truth and reconciliation process in which the reasons and deeds of the each party are post-hoc worked through.
It is true that a civil war is not constant fighting and life continues once the demarcation lines, like the Green Line in Beirut separating Muslim east Beirut from Christian west Beirut, are established especially if the fighting goes on for 15 years without a clear winner.
But it is somewhat suspicious that the Ta’if accord was agreed upon by all the warring factions which had been fighting each other to the teeth.
And this is where the kleptocracy begins in earnest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ta’if agreement changed the parliament to a 1-to-1 Muslim-Christian preassigned composition while strengthening the president.
Nevertheless, the previous agreements such as the predetermined religious affiliation of the speaker, president and prime minister was kept.
In essence, the militias partitioned the newly founded Lebanese state among themselves and created extreme rent-seeking mechanisms and patronage systems.
Ministries were distributed to the factional warlords and jobs were allotted along sectarian affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neo-liberal-post-war-order&quot;&gt;Neo-Liberal Post-War Order&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is are fairly run-of-the-mill corruption and has been replicated before and after the Ta’if agreement in many other countries.
But what made the Lebanese kleptocracy truly breath-taking is probably the largest Ponzi scheme and an entire national level in history that makes even Bernie Madoff look like an amateur.
It all boils down to the adage: Why rob a bank, if you can have one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to remember that the Lebanese state was basically run by different confessional parties which had crafted the political system in such a way that their grip on power could hardly be challenged.
This became especially evident during the 2022 elections, when new parties had to be signed off by the ruling system which obviously never allowed new parties to push them out of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rafic Hariri believed that the guarantor of growth for the Lebanese economy was the pegging of the Lebanese pound to the US dollar.
In a previous blog post I referred to the impossible trinity of economics: You can only choose two out of the following three: a stable exchange, a floating currency and sovereign economic policy.
The post civil war administration under Rafic Hariri chose to sacrifice economic sovereignty to keep the Lebanese pound at a stable exchange rate at around 1.500 LL to one dollar.
But since the national currency was floating, enough interest in the currency had to be generated to be able to keep the exchange rate.
Said differently, the central bank overseeing a currency pegged to the USD has to have considerable amounts of foreign exchange reserves to be able to exchange said currency at the fixed exchange rate at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lebanon had been living far beyond its means for a long time.
Trade balance had averaged from 2011 to 2019 between -20% and close to -30% while the fiscal balance went from -5% to -11% in the same time period.
The country was able to stave off the consequences on the exchange rate due to the large diaspora sending back remittances.
While Lebanon itself has around 6.8m citizens, the diaspora is estimated to be between 8m to 20m people which actively are in contact with their relatives.
This large diaspora sent back home over 7 billion USD, accounting up to 10% of GDP and providing a large steady influx of foreign currencies into the country.
But with the fall of oil prices in the 2010’s, the remittances of the Lebanese diaspora from the oil-rich gulf states diminished, leading to the first signs of the liquidity crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the banking sector had a weird skew as 1% of the accounts accounted for 50% of overall banking deposits yielding an extreme concentration.
Even better, 0.1% of accounts held 20% of all deposits at the banks inside Lebanon.
This was worrisome in its own right but raised the question who these accounts were.
If roughly 7.000 accounts controlled 20% of all deposits, this yields considerable control over the banks.
The banking sector was also concentrated in another manner, namely that the secondary debt market was very limited with 70% of all bank deposits invested in public sector and government securities.
In essence, the banks and the government were cozy with each other up to a worrying degree.
One could in fact ask whether the banking sector and the government were run by the same interest groups.
This does hark back to the proverb earlier about robbing versus owning a bank, as to how corrupt and nepotistic the banking sector in Lebanon actually was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-swap&quot;&gt;The ‘Swap’&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peg of the Lebanese pound became more strenuous to maintain with less and less hard currencies (Euros, Dollars, Yen, Francs etc) flowing into the country.
Remember that the official peg of ~1.500 LL to 1 USD forced the central bank to have sufficient foreign currencies on hand.
With the fissures in the foundation becoming apparent, the Banque du Liban went ape-shit neo-liberal at the extreme cost of the population to maintain the currency.
It started to serve the market instead of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Finance issued Eurobonds (remember the unregulated British offshore market) in foreign currencies while the Banque du Liban issued equivalently valued treasury bills denominated in Lebanese pound.
Remember that the foundation and goal was the pegged Lebanese pound and as a consequence both the Eurobonds and the TB’s were equivalent in value at least on paper.
In order to attract foreign currencies the Eurobonds offered a high interest rate up to 15% to guarantee that somebody would take the bonds off their hands.
The finance ministry and the central bank then swapped these bonds such that the central bank held the Eurobonds and the finance ministry the LL TB’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the central bank turned around and sold the Eurobonds on the open market receiving sought-after hard currencies in return.
But the government was still on the hook for the Eurobonds while the nominal USD value had been transferred to the central bank which was now happy that it had hard currencies again.
Who was unhappy you might ask?
The population the taxes of which were used to pay the high interest rates.
But who was the beneficiary of the high return on investment of the Lebanese Eurobonds?
The commercial banks who provided USD from the diasporas remittances and received a significant interest of up to 15%.
This encouraged the commercial banks with the diasporas USD to offer higher interest rates as well which set of a Ponzi scheme pulling in more USD dollar deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the central bank printed fresh Lebanese pounds depositing them at very low interest rates at the commercial banks, while allowing the commercial banks to deposit high interest deposits at the central bank.
In total the commercial banks had net liabilities of zero, as the central bank and commercial banks matched each other’s deposits.
But the central bank gave out significant higher interest with the round-tripping profit going as high as 11%.
Since Lebanese pound and USD were equivalent with the unsustainable peg, this amounted to 11% USD denominated profits.
Not bad, ey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the people of Lebanon got two raw ends of a deal with the corrupt sectarian political order.
The government had to spend a lot of precious foreign currency on pegging the currency instead of devaluing it which was done with tax payer money.
Secondly, after protests erupted in 2019 the banks closed for an unprecedented two weeks and upon reopening restricted the depositors access to their dollars.
While the black market exchange had already devaluated to a 1/10th of the value, the banks maintained the official peg thus giving their customers significantly less Lebanese pounds for each dollar.
This led to the coinage (pun intended) of the term ‘lollar’ with the abbreviation ‘lol’ as the Lebanese people could look at their Dollar statements but had no means of accessing them.
Most Lebanese have given up on the notion that they will one day recover their valuable dollar deposits as they have probably been pilfered to buy the treasury’s Eurobonds on which the government defaulted.
Thus the Dollars are most likely gone forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the nepotism and patronage in the entire sectarian economy this raises the strong case the commercial banks in Lebanon were obviously affiliated with the corrupt power brokers and used the central bank as printing press with USD denominated profits through the peg.
This entire financial engineering scheme amounted to little else than short-term fixes, ensuring that enough foreign currencies where in the country while paying out enormous interest rates to the commercial banks offering USD from the diaspora.
The IMF estimates that the Lebanese commercial banks participating in the scheme made off with 5 billion USD in profits at the expense of the tax payers with the central bank loosing up to 13 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why rob a bank, if you can rob an entire country with it? Preferably its central bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detailed reading, look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fdd.org/analysis/2020/08/04/crisis-in-lebanon/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; sophisticated article on the whole issue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">From the People, not For the People</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paris to Istanbul</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/ParisIstanbul2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paris to Istanbul" /><published>2022-09-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/ParisIstanbul2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/ParisIstanbul2022/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul001.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul001&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul001.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul001&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul001&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul001&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul001.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul001.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul002.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul002&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul002.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul002&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul002&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul002.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul002.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul003.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul003&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul003.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul003&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul003&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul003&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul003.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul003.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul201.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul201&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul201.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul201&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul201&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul201&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul201.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul201.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul202.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul202&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul202.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul202&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul202&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul202&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul202.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul202.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul203.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul203&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul203.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul203&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul203&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul203&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul203.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul203.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul209.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul209&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul209.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul209&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul209&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul209&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul209.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul209.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul210.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul210&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul210.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul210&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul210&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul210&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul210.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul210.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul219.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul219&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul219.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul219&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul219&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul219&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul219.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul219.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul220.jpg&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul220&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul220.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;parisistanbul220&quot; title=&quot;parisistanbul220&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;parisistanbul220&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul220.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul220.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/parisistanbul22/parisistanbul201.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Berlin Over The Years</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Berlin Over The Years" /><published>2022-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2022/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2201.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2201&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2201.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2201&quot; title=&quot;berlin2201&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2201&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2201.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2201.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2202.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2202&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2202.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2202&quot; title=&quot;berlin2202&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2202&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2202.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2202.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2203.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2203&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2203.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2203&quot; title=&quot;berlin2203&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2203&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2203.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2203.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2204.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2204&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2204.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2204&quot; title=&quot;berlin2204&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2204&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2204.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2206.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2206&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2206.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2206&quot; title=&quot;berlin2206&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2206&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2206.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2206.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2207.jpg&quot; title=&quot;berlin2207&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2207.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;berlin2207&quot; title=&quot;berlin2207&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;berlin2207&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2207.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2207.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2022/berlin2201.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Portugal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Portugal2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portugal" /><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Portugal2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Portugal2022/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/1.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;1&quot; title=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/2.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;2&quot; title=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/3.jpg&quot; title=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/3.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;3&quot; title=&quot;3&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/4.jpg&quot; title=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/4.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;4&quot; title=&quot;4&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/5.jpg&quot; title=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/5.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;5&quot; title=&quot;5&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/5.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/5.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/6.jpg&quot; title=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/6.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;6&quot; title=&quot;6&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/6.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/6.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/7.jpg&quot; title=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/7.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;7&quot; title=&quot;7&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/7.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/7.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/8.jpg&quot; title=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/8.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;8&quot; title=&quot;8&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/8.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/8.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/9.jpg&quot; title=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/9.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;9&quot; title=&quot;9&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/9.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/portugal22/9.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">Porto and the North Coast</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/portugal22/4.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Off-Shore Finance Centers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Off-Shore Finance Centers" /><published>2022-06-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters/">&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the Tax Justice Network published a ground breaking &lt;a href=&quot;https://fsi.taxjustice.net&quot;&gt;ranking&lt;/a&gt; which evaluated countries on how much financial secrecy they provided to somebody who wanted to move their money and wealth undisturbed across the world and free from democratic and/or governmental oversight.
The biggest surprise back then was the country on top of the list, while the succeeding ranks were populated by the usual suspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2008, the list has changed a bit as for example Singapore has moved up significantly.
The reason for that is that it fulfills the little hinterland requirement, a strong rule of law and a good integration into the global economy.
Especially Swiss banks are preparing for a stricter financial secrecy regulation in Europe and the US, and have picked Singapore with even stricter bank secrecy laws as their contingency jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurpringly, the usual suspects were present in the Tax Justice Network Financial Secrecy Ranking but the number one spot might surprise you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Cayman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Switzerland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Luxembourg&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) US&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, how did US come out on top?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s go through the list step by step …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uk&quot;&gt;UK&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an entire blog post dedicated to the rise of the British offshore system.
Arguably, the British were the midwifes of the offshore financial system through the City of London.
The offshore and EuroMarket system would have probably developed any way as the interests of the financial sector for less regulation and oversight are are found in every country.
It just so happened that the UK was the birthplace due to its strongly developed financial services industry from times of the mighty British empire and its especially lax regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British offshore system is organized in a hub-and-spoke system where the City of London sits in the middle.
It represents the spider in a world wide spiders web that serve as conduit of clandestine money.
A full 1/3 of all offshore wealth is deposited in the former colonies and Crown dependencies of the UK.
Add the City of London to it and the a full 1/2 of all offshore wealth is domiciled in the former British empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, while the British themselves on their rainy island were busy creating the EuroMarket, the Caribbean offshore industry was developed in close cooperation with American lawyers and accountants.
This was mainly due to the close proximity of the US to the pleasant weather which made a quick deposit of secret money in your favorite Caribbean bank account pleasant and convenient.
In fact the first shell company legislation was written on the British Virgin Islands in 1976 by an American lawyer called Paul Butler in cooperation with Neville Westwood and Michael Riegels.
The crux of the story is regulatory capture as corporate lawyers on Wall Street essentially drafted the International Business Companies Act to the maximum liking of the American customers.
Thus the BVI commercialized their sovereignty to Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;switzerland&quot;&gt;Switzerland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Schweizerische Eidgenossenschaft’ has constructed its entire political identity around the notion of neutrality, grass-roots democracy and non-interference.
It thus serves as international neutral ground on which many global organizations have their headquarters and provides services typical of an entrepot or international conduit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swiss federation has put increased emphasis on local governments of the 26 cantons to administer their communities according to their liking.
This follows the Swiss idea of direct democracy in which many issues are decided upon through referendums.
This direct democracy was the reason why the Swiss federation agreed only in 1971 to grant women the voting right.
But it would take another 20 years to 1991 for the last canton Appenzell Innerrhoden to fully implement female suffrage following a law suit by women from this canton.
This was a direct outgrowth of the independent, localized legislation that is a hallmark of Swiss political identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switzerland’s neutrality was guaranteed at the Congress of Vienna, where the aristocracy of Europe redistributed the continent among themselves after the civil revolution originating from the French revolution in 1792.
The formalization of Swiss neutrality induced an influx of capital where the Italians banked in Lugano, the French in Geneva and the Germans in Zurich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The huge financial burden of World War I led to a ten fold increase, as all belligerent countries raised taxes during and after the war.
From 1920 to 1929, the annual growth was 14% which coinceded with the 1920-21 and 1925-27 French tax increases.
Following the world financial crisis in 1929, the annual growth fell to only 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the World Financial Crisis 1929, the lower and middle class populace of Switzerland was rightfully so angry at the banks for as they were made responsible for the repercussions felt by the population.
While banking secrecy had already existed in Switzerland, it had merely been encoded in the civil law, meaning that the state wouldn’t prosecute it.
With the increased scrutiny by the Swiss public towards their dealings, the banking and business circles wanted to make sure that the Swiss state wouldn’t get any supervisional rights.
What was even worse to them, was that the supervision could include some sort of privy into the bank-client relationship.
THus they enforced the banking secrecy legislation in the criminal law.
The drafting of the law started in 1933 whereas the idea of stricter regulation started as early as 1931.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that occured as a direct consequence of the financial crisis 1929 and the subsequent public outrage resulting in the passage of the law in 1934.
This stands in direct opposition to the idea that Swiss bank secrecy was enshrined to protect the wealth of Jews from the Nazis which is honestly a lie by the Swiss public opinion.
The were just as anti-semitic as everybody else in Europe and even made Swiss jews pay for the costs of taking on Jews flewing from the Nazis and seeking refuge in Switzerland.
From 1933 to 1945, only 1.5% of all new accounts were in fact Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Switzerland became an international point of attraction for flight capital due to its favourable financial conditions, the cantons inside Switzerland competed for the flight capital just the way Switzerland competed on an international stage.
Remember that each canton in Switzerland has a fair amount of leeway on what kind of laws it wants to pass.
Thus the cantons started a race to the bottom, undercutting each other in the hopes of attracting more of the money flowing into Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the canton of Zug hosts 27.000 corporations: 4 for every one of its inhabitants.
The extreme imbalance of hidden wealth to people results in another intersting statistic: although the Swiss population comprises only 0.1% of the world population, a full 1/3 of American stock market is held by Swiss banks for its costumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When money flows into a country, it is idealistically converted to the local currency when it crosses the border.
This generates a demand for the local currency.
In Switzerland’s case this in fact changed the sign of the interest rate banks charge you for taking your money.
Normally, banks are happy to store your money as it gives them capital to lend it out at a higher rate.
But in Switzerlands case the central bank of Switzerland started to charge -0.75% for all banks lending money from them, starting from 2015.
By 2022 they reduced it to -0.25% as the interest in the Swiss franc as a stable safe haven waned.
But it will probably increase again as spectre of inflation haunts all of the major currencies.
A nice side effect implemented by the Swiss banks is that the negative interest rates are only applied to savings account such that customers are encouraged to move their wealth to the wealth management division.
But obviously that’s only viable for rich people, so the poor loose out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;luxembourg&quot;&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grand Duchy has paralyzed the EU’s fight against offshore finance like a very active sleeper agent in the center of Europe between Germany and France.
It was a founding member of the European Union at the Treaty of Rome in 1957.
But since then, it has changed dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that Luxembourg does not owe its success in offshore finance to its so-called stability or highly skilled workforce.
What is has to offer as its modern history is a story of a regulatory capture and the cautionary tale of an entrenched elite.
The royal family has maintained on the throne since 1783 which is impressive given the tumultuous centuries thereafter.
More importantly the Christian Social Peoples Party has provided the prime minister since WWII except for five years in the 1970’s and after the election of 2013.
This is similar to the Isle of Jersey in which the ruling elite has created a micro-cosmos in which everybody knows everybody and anybody not toeing the plutocratic line is ostracized immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does owe its success in international finance to its utter selling out of its sovereignty to the highest bidder.
In the 1970s, this little state of 500.000 people started selling a truely new product to multinational companies: the explicit offer to let them choose their own taxation, regulatory constraints and legal obligations.
Does a big international bank want to set up a new multi-billion fund?
Let them decide their own tax rate, effectively 0% on profits. Nice.
Does the same bank want to sell securities to raise cash and satisfy the capital requirements of another country’s regulators?
Let the bank create their own ‘hybrid securities’ which act as securities to regulators and as debt to the tax department, thus making their profits deductible from the corporate income tax. Convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation and servicing of the holding structures, shell companies and multinational registration requires a significant workforce.
In Luxembourg, 150.000 people commute every day from France, Belgium and Germany into the Grand Duchy with a population of a mere 500.000.
This greatly distorts macro economic statistics, as the gross domestic product is only 2/3 of the gross national product, after subtracting the wages paid to the commuting workforce from the neighboring countries and the dividends and interest to the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anybody arguing that hypertropic financial sectors lift all economic boats in a country should look at Luxembourg.
GDP per worker has grown only 1.4% per year, which was essentially wiped out by inflation every year.
Salaries in the offshore finance industry and business consulting have exploded, implicitly at the cost of other countries tax revenue, while manufacturing, transportation and construction workers have not seen any real wage increase in twenty years.
Luxembourg has essentially pushed its lower class into the neighboring countries which now commute to work from France, Germany and Belgium as well.
The poverty in Luxembourg has doubled since 1980 as all the tax cuts to the cheapest bidder have impacted basically everybody not working in offshore finance.
The tax cutes and externalization of its work force has left the educational system in shambles as Luxembourg performs among the worst in the OECD club and scholastic inequality is among the highest.
Housing prices have tripled in a country with little to show for except a castle and Luxembourg city is now as expensive as London which mops the floor with Luxembourg City in terms of basic attractions of an interesting city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why hasn’t the EU done anything about a brazen offshore centre in its middle which has sold its sovereignty to the cheapest bidder while enjoying and living off the advantage of the European Union?
A birth defect of the EU is that every member obtains a veto right which allows Luxembourg to torpedo any advance in combating offshore finance in the EU itself.
With the secret meetings of the European Council, a plutocratic prime minister of a country with a bare 500.000 inhabitants and with little to show for in terms of a genuine economy can dictate terms on the 500 million people of the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;usa&quot;&gt;USA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the United States have become the most accommodating country to money which likes to move around the world in the shadows.
Three main reasons stand out in the US top rank in the Financial Secrecy Index: the federalist political structure, its pro-business, deregulated environment after neoliberalism became a bon-mot in the 1980’s and the therefrom originating power of Wall Street over Washington DC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1981, it was becoming evident that the advance of the unregulated EuroMarket couldn’t be stopped.
US banks had already overrun London with local branches and had quickly become the major players in the London EuroMarket.
So instead of trying to fight it, US regulators started to imitate it with International Banking Facilities (IBF).
Similar to offshore banking in London, IBFs exist in the physical offices of US banks, but everything is separated from the US operations books.
Thus the banks have to set of books on the same desk: one for the US operations and one for the unregulated offshore market.
IBFs can offer deposit and loan services only to non-US residents and institutions.
More importantly, the offshore books are free of the reserve requirements of the US Federal Reserve and thus generate more profit.
The IBF’s were proposed in 1978 in a direct attempt to stem the flow of money from the US into the offshore market.
The Japanese quickly followed with the Japanese Offshore Markets (JOM) and thus the three big financial centers of the world all embraced the unregulated offshore market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The states of Delaware, Wyoming, South Dakota and Nevada have worked hard to be as welcoming as possible to money, the origin of which nobody should know of.
It all started with Delaware, which is small, yet unremarkable state in search of a new source of revenue.
The chemical giant DuPont basically ruled over Delaware from its headquarters in the capital of Wilmington.
Thus a very large company resided in the a very small state which gave the big corporation significant sway through its sheer size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the economy become sluggish in the 1980’s, a deregulation of interest rates was proposed to attract banking business.
In fact, the backers of a new deregulation bill on interest rate caps sought to emulate Luxembourg and become its version in the United States.
Very quickly, the big banks noticed the removed restriction on interest rates and rushed into the state.
South Dakota did something similar and removed its usury laws with a statute which was basically written by CitiBank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of Delaware quickly realized how much business it could attract given its inconspicuous size, if allowed companies more leeway and deregulated basically all restrictions away.
They quickly hopped onto the shell company wagon as they observed the rise of the Caribbean offshore financial centers.
With talks ramping up in the 1980’s between the UK and China on the repatriation of Hong Kong, Delaware trade delegations heavily courted the Hong Kong.
This is a somewhat amusing story since the number 8 is considered lucky in Chinese culture and Delaware beat the drum for incorporating Chinese holding companies on August 8, 1988.
But the British Virgin Islands did the same thing by keeping offices open on its Emancipation Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas the infamous Ugland hous in the Cayman Islands holds 12.000 corporations, one office in Delaware alone holds 217.000 companies.
In fact, Delaware is so popular, that 1209 North Orange Street is in the legal sense the home of Ford, GM, Coca-Cola, KFC, Intel, Google, HP and Texas Instruments all managed by Corporation Trust, a subsidiary of the Dutch Firm Wolters-Kluwer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 80’s, Delaware has risen to the preeminent location of anonymous shell companies in the US.
Wyoming, South Dakota and Nevada have quickly followed suit by facilitating the creation of companies and requiring little to no information on the incorporation of companies.
In fact Nevada does not even share tax or incorporation information the the federal state allowing the formation of, for all intents and purposes, secret companies right in the middle of the United States.
South Dakota has specialized in trusts and literally does not share information on trusts formed within its state boundaries.
So essentially, one could create a trust, accumulate enormous sums of money in that trust and nobody would actually know about it.
Imagine a, for example, five billion USD heavy trust under the control of an unknown person and whose existence is not known to the public.
The problem is in fact that nobody knows how much money resides in South Dakota trusts, as they are per law shrouded in secrecy.
Nevada and Wyoming require no identification documents on who the principal owner of a shell corporation is.
For the company director, you can simply pay anybody 20 USD to put their name on the filings and you got your company.
When you search for company formation agents in Nevada and the like you usually get prices starting at 249 depending on the type of corporate entity you want to have.
For 249 USD you get a company, add another 150 USD for a Nevada nominee officer and your name disappears from the registration thus giving you a perfect anonymous shell company.
For 949 USD you get the premium package and get an anonymous shell company equipped with a bank account.
Thus you can start your shady dealings right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then take that anonymous company and open a bank account at your local bank and start transferring money into the United States.
With that money you can buy luxury real estate or super expensive cars to park you money or sell it again later to get money from a valid transaction instead of for example selling cocaine.
Thus these companies are used to launder dirty money right in the United States.
If the authorities come knocking on your door, they have no way to know who really controls the shell company that you used to launder the money.
It could be Kim Jong-Un’s dictatorship, the LosZetas cartel from Mexico or the Iranian Revolutionary Guard.
You literally can’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now obviously it’s a bit suspicious if a company gets incorporated and immediately starts dealing with eight to nine figure transactions.
This is why incorporation agents in Delaware, Nevada and Wyoming offer aged or shelved companies which give of a more serious vibe through having existed at least on paper for multiple years.
These are usefull for fraud, as people tend to believe that companies that are multiple years old must have a somewhat reliable business model.
Yet again these are pure shell companies but you can have one for only 299 USD.
Who said money laundering has to be expensive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">Secrecy Jurisdictions World Wide Inc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Off-Shore Finance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Off-Shore Finance" /><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance/">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt; MathJax.Hub.Config({ TeX: { equationNumbers: { autoNumber: &quot;all&quot; } } }); &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt;
         MathJax.Hub.Config({
           tex2jax: {
             inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], [&quot;\\(&quot;,&quot;\\)&quot;] ],
             displayMath: [['$$','$$']],
             processEscapes: true
           }
         });
       &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;origins&quot;&gt;Origins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Second World War was entering its final stage as the attendees of the Bretton Woods conference convened to determine the post war financial order of the world.
The influx of money into the United States due to World War I and the loans of the yet unfinished World War 2 made the US hold close to half of all gold reserves world wide.
This made them yield considerable power money wise entering the negotiations in a world in which all currencies had a gold peg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the impossible trinity (pick two out of three) of stable exchange rates, economic sovereignty and free capital, the representatives of the attending nations decided to impose capital controls on its citizens in favour of stable currencies and macro-economic sovereignty.
This essentially restricted banks to only do business in their respective countries as money could not leave a country on a whim or at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a severe blow to the bankers in the City of London which had been accustomed to banking in the economic sphere of the British empire.
It put the City of London into a comatose state as there wasn’t enough business to do for the banks which had previously serviced the financial needs in an empire encompassing close to a quarter of the worlds populations at its peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the British banking establishment, the Bank of England was more supporter than regulator as everybody knew everybody else in the upper echelons of British society.
The attendance of exclusive private schools and the shared reminiscence of the might of the British empire instilled a sense of entitlement that the internationally agreed upon laws did not apply to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus when the USD from the Soviet foreign banks started to being lent out by British banks, the British regulators were happy that international banking had returned to England.
These dollars that circulated outside the control of the Federal Reserve that was responsible for them were called EuroDollars.
In 1963 the first EuroBonds were sold which were unregulated bearer bonds.
Now bearer bonds are the perfect tool for tax evasion and money laundering.
Essentially the are like an ultra valuable dollar bill with a worth of whatever the issuer thinks fits his needs.
No record is kept of their purchase or sale as they are unregulated.
Thus you can buy them in one part of the onshore financial system, cross any border you want with the piece of ultra valuable unregulated paper, and sell it somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money for the exploding EuroBonds market came from all the hidden money stashed away in the Swiss bank vaults.
If you have money in numbered bank accounts in Switzerland you’re definitely happy that your money is safe.
But at the same it could be working for you, being lent out to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The German banker Siegmund Warburg and Scottish war hero Ian Fraser organized a quite dizzying setup to ensure that the bonds they were issuing skirted around every possible regulation and went through every imaginable loop hole.
Often these financial products used different quirks in different European countries to their advantage to remain as unregulated as possible, something called regulatory arbitrage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first EuroBonds by Siegmund Warburg were formally issued in Schiphol airport in the Netherlands.
They paid their interest in Luxembourg, free of charge.
They were listed on the London Stock Exchange.
And the borrower was officially the Italian Autostrade, an Italian state motorway company, while it was in fact the Italian IRI state holding company.
All while being a bearer bond as it was registered and regulated nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there the EuroMarkets exploded in all directions right under the pathetic nose of the Bank of England which was actively doing nothing, happy that business was flowing again in London.
Business, which economists and politicians had prudently and wisely restricted through capital controls to shield the real economy from financial crashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1960 the EuroMarket which were mostly USD sloshing outside the US was worth 1 Billion, ten years later in 1970 it was already 46 Billion USD.
In 1971 Nixon abolished the Gold standard which effectively initiated the decline of Bretton Woods.
Together with the shift towards a more neoliberal stance, capital control were revoked starting in 1973 and by 1979 effectively all capital controls were gone.
By 1980 the EuroMarket had thus ballooned to 500 Billion, and surging to 2.6 Trillion in 1988.
It should be noted that EuroMarket quickly came to encompass any freely movable currency besides the USD that one could think of.
So in 1997 the EuroMarket centered on London represented 90% of all international loans TI92.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wealth-in-off-shore-finance-system&quot;&gt;Wealth in Off Shore Finance System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to estimate the amount of wealth that is stored in the offshore financial center as the purpose of offshore is to remain hidden and untraceable.
Gabriel Zucman estimates it to be around 8% of all wealth.
The way he proceeds is to analyze the liabilities-holdings gap when comparing international statistical data on wealth.
If you had a secret bank account you would most likely want your money to do something, like be invested in stocks.
It turns out that 1/3 of the American stock market is held by Swiss bank accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume a British person has hid wealth in Switzerland and tasked his Swiss bank to buy stocks in the US.
What American statisticians see is that American stock is held by foreigners, which is marked as a liability.
In Switzerland nothing is recorded, as the bank is merely holding the stocks not owning them.
In the UK, no assets are recorded as the British persons wants his stock ownership to be kept secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now normally the assets and liabilities should cancel each other out, as something being owned by a foreigner in one country should pop up as the property of that foreigner in his home country.
But there is a massive hole valued at 7.6 trillion USD, which represents 8% of the global wealth, which is unaccounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is Luxembourg as the second largest incorporater of mutual funds.
The regulators in Luxembourg say that 3.5 trillion USD are owned via shares in Luxembourg.
But when you scour the statistics worldwide, one can only find 1.5 trillion USD officially registered in Luxembourg which means that 2 trillion USD are unaccounted for, held by people who do not want to claim their ownership of mutual fund shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;secrecy-jurisdictions&quot;&gt;Secrecy Jurisdictions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people think about offshore finance and tax havens, they usually think of rich people not wanting to pay taxes.
This is most certainly true but above all these offshore financial centers are secrecy jurisdictions, in which nobody knows what’s actually happening.
A side effect is that if you don’t know that somebody parked his or her wealth somewhere, then you also can’t tax it.
Another big draw for offshore centers is their prevalent deregulation, to the point of regulatory castration, in a laissez-faire approach to economics with which most economic historians will strongly disagree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way the rich, powerful, crooked or greedy (or any combination thereof) like to secure, hide and defend their wealth is through three main tools: trusts in the Anglo-Saxon sphere, foundations and shell companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trusts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trusts are a patriarchic quirk of British law dating back to the dark ages.
Back then, when a men went on the crusades, he obviously wasn’t home to defend his estate and property.
And because women weren’t allowed to hold land, he signed his property over to a friend who remained back in England.
The crusader would be the trust settlor, the friend staying in England the trustee and the wife and kids of the crusader were the beneficiaries.
Thus the ownership was signed over to the trustee with the clear purpose that the trustee manages the property and assets in a way to benefit the beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, trusts have lost their patriarchic purpose but now serve the nefarious purpose of hiding and defending secret wealth.
The main purpose of a trust in our time is to protect wealth from taxation, regulators and creditors.
They are created through the legal fiction of separating ownership from control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that reason they are for example very popular with rich Muslims.
Islam declares having a mortgage and an insurance policy as haram, as planning out for the future goes against Allah’s divine plan and him taking care of you as a pious Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides cultural sensibilities, the sparsity of law and regulation make trusts very popular for wealth management.
They are not taxed as entities, but are taxed where the trustee is registered.
In a peculiar twist, offshore financial centers offer 0% tax rate on trusts and consequentially on trustees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the trustee is the legally liable person of the assets parked in the trust, creditors and regulators who might be after the trust settlor’s assets can’t touch the assets as the settlor has ceded ownership to the trustee.
And if you want to be really cautious, you can insert the OFC speciality of ‘flee clauses’ into a trust agreement.
Should anybody come knocking on a trustee’s door or should more favourable terms be viable elsewhere, the trust can change legal registration in the blink of an eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English law foresaw the restriction on perpetuity, as they did not want assets accumulating in trusts.
Over time, these accumulating assets could possibly give the trust structure outsized economic might and increase social inequality.
Thus they were limited to 99 years to prevent economic dynasties.
Guess what the offshore centers did: they abolished these rules.
But Wyoming and South Dakota did the same thing, so it’s not only the Brits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal advantage of trusts is that the law defines trusts as ‘a fidicuary relationship with respect to property’.
Importantly, such a relationship can be defined in any way possible, allowing for multitudes of special arrangement.
But even more importantly, the beneficiaries and the trust itself is nowhere recorded.
So you can theoretically move 5 billion USD into an offshore trust, name your kids the beneficiaries and the tax men wouldn’t even know.
This obscurity and outright secrecy makes trusts so appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time there is the thorny issue of the trustee which you have to pick carefully.
When offshore centers tried to vie for Asian ultra hight net worth (UHNW) individuals, they quickly realized that most Asian patriarchs were loath to relinquish control over their companies to a trustee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the British Virgin Islands VISTA structures were developed.
The Virgin Islands Special Trust Act (VISTA) removed any duties, obligations and liabilities from the trustee.
See, normally the trustee is liable for the successful managing of the assets put into the trust.
This includes running an entire company, if the settlor so chose to park an entire company in the trust.
With VISTA, the trustee only role is to be a placeholder for the owner of the company, while it is run by the settlor.
Another innovation, if you want to call it that, was the creation of the protector role which allows the protector chosen by the settlor to remove and reassign trustee roles.
While not really necessary for wealth managers of UHNWI’s as they are usually professionals, it does give more power to the settlor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cayman Islands Special Trust Alternative Regime (STAR) innovated by removing the constraint of having people being the sole beneficiaries of a trust.
STAR trusts expanded the purpose of a trust to literally anything, increasing the beneficiaries wealth or even political goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundations are popular for a similar reasons as VISTA and STAR trusts as they give the creator a lot of leeway.
They are predominantly used by rich people from BRICS (the emerging markets Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa) countries, where wealth generation has been immense, but the formation of general trust not so much.
Similar to Asian rich people from low trust countries, they also loathe the idea of relinquishing control to strangers.
But with foundations, the founder has signatory authority on the foundation’s bank accounts, giving him full control.
For example, Panama has developed itself into the center for Latin American wealth management, as Latin Americans have experienced much political unrest and have high force inheritance laws.
Thus they want to protect their wealth without ceding control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Merriam-Webster dictionary, a foundation is ‘funds given for the permanent support of an institution’ or ‘an organization or institution established by endowment with provision for future maintenance’.
Funnily enough, the definition goes on citing directly an offshore wealth management technique by naming ‘a trust administered by a foundation’ as an example.
While most people attribute philanthropic ideals to a foundation, by law it is just assets and money given for the support of a specific cause for future generations.
So in reality the purpose of a foundation can be anything the founder wants it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big advantage of foundations in terms of maintaining control is that the founder can be both beneficiary of the foundation and be the director of the council of the foundation.
Coupled with the signatory authority, the founder can have maximum control over what happens with and inside a foundation.
Also, assets can be moved in and out of a foundation, making it a flexible asset protection structure.
Additionally, a foundation can open bank accounts and go into contracts.
Compared to trusts which are a British common law structure and aren’t recognized by civil law, foundations are universally accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside compared to trusts is that they have to be registered as a legal person, making them more visible than trusts.
But Panama and the Seychelles already offer foundations with nominee founders such that the names of the real founders are in the dark again.
Due to the public registration, administrative costs of foundations are higher, as bylaws and articles have to be formulated and they are usually audited.
Also, transferring wealth into foundations can be taxed in most onshore countries and as a legal person a foundation can be sued and go bankrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shell Companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to trusts, which are only recognized in common law countries, and foundations which have to hold up to public/governmental scrutiny, companies are universally recognized as legal entities.
Similarly to foundations they can exist in perpetuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US have vigorously defended their spot on the top of the Financial Secrecy Index, shell companies can be bought for as little as 250 USD in states like Nevada, Wyoming and Delaware.
In the more advanced secrecy jurisdictions they come with the extra flavour of nominee directors, which keep the beneficial owner’s name off the records.
For the registration, these secrecy jurisdictions don’t require identification, but the company does require directors.
So the nominee directors serve as directors for the shell company while doing absolutely nothing in terms of real managing of the company.
There is a story of a 23 year old fast food cook who was the nominee director of a New Zealand company.
The 20 USD he was paid were quite nice until international prosecutors knocked on his door, asking him why he was the director of an arms smuggling company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage is that companies can open bank accounts and that credit cards can be given out on those accounts.
Barclays, a British bank, had to admit that close to 19% of its credit cards were linked to bank accounts in tax havens registered to shell companies.
Thus, presumably, the beneficial owners moved their wealth into tax havens, set up a shell company with a bank account, and then used a credit card on the shell company’s bank account to go shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some jurisdictions even offer bearer shares which is a stupendous money laundering tool.
The transactions of bearer shares are recorded nowhere and the person who is the bearer of the share is the owner of it.
But legally, the owner of those bearer shares can say under oath that as long as he’s not physically holding the share in his hand, that he’s not the owner of the company.
So imagine a company laundering money and the police comes asking the supposed owner of the company, who’s exerting control over the company via bearer shares, whether he owns the company or not.
Then the owner, who’s doing money laundering, can say ‘No’ and thats legally valid.
Offshore is a weird world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell companies are hid behind the lawyer-client privilege as a lawyer is used as the front man.
This adds another lawyer of obfuscation since the name of the true owner of a shell company can’t be divulged by force.
Thus, if the police comes knocking, the lawyer is protected from having to name the true owner of the company as it would violate the lawyer-client confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, wealth and companies are placed in a trust-company structure.
The company allows maximum flexibility and access to the parked wealth by offering credit cards and being able to move assets in and out of the company.
The shares of the company are then put into a trust with a nominee.
Thus the owner of the wealth and the onshore corporation can do whatever he or she wants.
But in case the tax authority wants to inquire who all this wealth belongs to, the trust arrangement legally separates the settlor from is assets.
Similarly, creditors can’t access the company assets as they belong to the trust and not the settlor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Limited Liability Partnerships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your business interests can also be incorporated into a Limited Liability Partnership which are ‘tax transparent’.
First of all, partnerships are subject to far less scrutiny than real companies, as only the partners have money in them.
Thus only the partners money is involved and not the publics.
Stock companies are more transparent as the public can invest in them so they are held to more stringent standards.
Thus partnerships are in general more opaque as nobody but the partners have their money in them.
But traditionally, partners were also on the hook should something go awry.
Also, partnerships are taxed on a per partner basis, such that any profits or losses the partnerships accrues is passed directly onto the partners.
Thus profits and losses are directly taxed with the individual partners, making the tax transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited Liability Partnerships (LLP) were created on behest of the big four accounting firms on the Isle of Jersey as they wanted to have the cake and eat it too.
So they wanted the opaqueness and maximal profit of a partnership with the protection of a separate legal entity which would be on the hook instead of the partners.
In a normal partnership, if the business decisions go sour, the partners are on the hook as their share of the partnership makes them legally responsible.
For example, if an accounting firm screws up while auditing and the audited company goes belly up, the partners of the accounting firm would be directly responsible for possible law suits by damaged share holders of stock companies.
Partnerships would ensure that the partners of the accounting firm would have skin in the game thus forcing them to be stringent.
Limited Liability Partnerships do away with such precautions and the accounting firms can happily screw up without fearing the repercussions: fees for me, losses for the public. Hurray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-of-tax-havens&quot;&gt;Advantages of Tax Havens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas the creation of the EuroMarket served the purpose of moving money into a less regulated sphere where it could generate more profits free from capital controls, the origin of tax havens is more muddled.
Ostensibly, their original purpose was the provision of low tax and preferential tax regimes, but early on they put an increased emphasis on secrecy for individuals.
Meyer Lansky had deep ties to the Bahamas and used them to launder money for the mob.
Many of the trust regulations were aimed at people hiding their wealth as much from their families as from the tax authorities.
In general, tax havens offered secrecy jurisdiction perks, of which tax evasion was a natural consequence since you can’t tax what you can’t see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multinational enterprises (MNE) are one of the financial players which use the preferential tax regimes of tax havens extensively.
When people talk about tax evasion or tax avoidance, most of the lost tax revenues is due to multinationals not paying appropriate taxes.
With the globalization of economies, many supply chains stretch across half the world.
In fact 2/3 of all trade is done within multinationals as they move products and components over their supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way multinationals cheat on governments tax revenue is through ‘transfer pricing’.
Many multinationals have subsidiaries registered in different countries which sell components to each other as products move along the supply chain.
Imagine that the iPhone is developed in a high tax country such as the US and sold by the sales department which is registered in a low tax country.
The development division can sell the iPhone for a low price to the sales department thereby making only little profit in the high tax country.
This creates a loss for the development division as R&amp;amp;D and production is expensive and they are selling the products cheaply.
The sales department then sells the iPhone for the original price but as its registered in a low tax country such as Luxembourg or Ireland, there is only little tax on its profits.
The mother company, Apple, thus pockets the difference in the tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transfer pricing has led to some astonishing price mechanisms.
Examples are water plastic seals from the Czech Republic to the parent company for 972.98 USD per unit, gloves from China for 4,121.81 USd a kilo and locks from France for 3,067.17 per Kilo.
These import prices made the parent companies in the US overpay such they reduced their profits on which they could be taxed.
Exports from the US were stupendously low as missiles exported to Israel were priced at 52.03 USD a piece, diamonds were exported to India at 13.45 USD carat, cameras were suddenly worth 7.44 USD when exported to Colombia and car seats were exported for a mere 1.66 USD to Belgium.
So when the US parent company sold something, these were priced very low as it crossed the border to a subsidiary in another country.
The parent company in the US made little profit which incurred little absolute taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google for example sold the IP of its search engine algorithm to an Irish subsidiary to which it pays licensing fees.
The fees are costs for the US operations, thus diminishing the corporate tax rate, and increasing profits for the low tax Irish subsidiary.
Similar schemes have led Ireland have trade surplus of 25% of its GDP which grossly distorts macro economic numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect is the complete disregard for prudent finance and financial safeguards in offshore financial centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe for offshore financial centers, every country has capital requirements for banks.
These capital requirements stipulate that a bank or financial institution has to keep a certain percentage of its assets as cash such that if the assets go bad, the financial corporation can offset the loss immediately with the cash reserves and is not endangered by the sudden loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these cash requirements are understandably cumbersome for the financial companies as it is money they can’t put to use to generate profits.
Offshore financial centers are attractive insofar as they reduce financial prudence to a minimum and require very little capital requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes interesting once we look at how credit increases the money supply.
Most money is actually not printed by the central banks but generated through credit.
A bank never actually has all the money of all the depositors on hand at all times but only has a little amount at its immediate disposal to fulfill the withdrawals of customers.
Most of the money is tied up in long term loans and only because only a few customers withdraw all their money at once allows the bank to keep functioning with only little cash at hand.
If all customers would withdraw their money all at once, due to a loss of faith in the bank safekeeping their wealth, we would have a bank run and the bank wouldn’t be able to pay out all its depositors and panic would ensue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets assume that we have 100 USD, and the capital requirement $r$ is 10%.
This means we have to keep 10% in cash at our bank and are allowed to loan out 90% to another financial player.
The second party now has 90 USD and can in turn make loans to a third party with the remaining 81 USD once the 9 USD cash is kept.
The third party now gets 81 USD and can give out 72.9 USD in a new loan after subtracting the 10% capital requirement.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
M_1 &amp;= M_0 *(1-r) &amp;&amp;= 90 \\
M_2 &amp;= M_1 * (1-r) = 100 * (1-r)^2 &amp;&amp;= 81 \\
M_3 &amp;= M_2 * (1-r) = 100 * (1-r)^3 &amp;&amp;= 72.9 \\
M_4 &amp;= \ldots
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
This forms a geometric series and if we were to continue to infinity, we’d get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
M_\infty = \sum_k^\infty M_0 \cdot (1-r)^k = \frac{M_0}{r}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With $r=10%$ we increase the money supply tenfold but more importantly we create a chain of dependencies in terms of credit.
By reducing the capital requirements we make every financial institution more susceptible to defaults, the chain along which the money bounces through the system longer and ultimately the entire system more fragile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offshore finance centres are appealing to the financial system as transactions are done in almost complete darkness due to the lack of oversight.
Additionally, extremely restrained regulation basically results in little financial prudence i.e. very low capital requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in a ballooning amount of EuroDollars created in this offshore market and an almost impenetrable interdependence between financial institutions.
It is thus no wonder that the offshore markets were a great amplifier, conduit and cause of the financial crises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem in offshore financial markets is the proliferation of special purpose vehicles (SPV) that are created by their parent companies.
The sole purpose of these subsidiary legal entities is to separate the risk of ventures in the SPV from the parent company.
The assets do not appear on the balance sheet of the parent company and SPV’s have their own assets, liabilities and financial statements, yet the business decisions are made by the parent company.
Upon creation, the rules and purpose of these vehicles are clearly defined and it receives funding from investors to buy the agreed-upon assets in its creation document.
The lendors to the SPV can buy bonds or shares of the SPV and the worth of the SPV is defined by the assets it bought from the raised funds.
Mostly, SPVs are used for securitization, such that interest payments far into the future can be monetized into a lump sum that the originator of the security can book now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enron used special purpose vehicles (SPV) in the Bahamas to offload debt.
They sold their debt to specifically designed SPV’s, such that their debt was offloaded into the Caribbean ocean.
Since their financial statements were separate from Enron itself, the parent company in Houston could claim to be in superb financial health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Northern Rock used the Granite SPV to offload mortgages into the offshore world and clean its balance sheet.
The Granite SPV eventually grew to 50 billion USD but was hidden from regulators as the position did not occur on the balance sheet.
The creation of SPVs in offshore financial markets is so popular due to their laxer regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the reason why the Bahamas claim to have 75% of the worlds hedge funds incorporated within their jurisdiction.
Long-Term Capital Management for example was incorporated in the Bahamas and executed their massively leveraged investment strategy from there.
AIG Financial Products that almost tanked the insurance giant all on its own by selling Credit Default Swaps to everybody asking was located in the City of London.
These are just a few examples in which the non-existent regulation of offshore financial markets have resulted in massive collateral damage to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-for-tax-havens&quot;&gt;Advantages for Tax Havens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax havens themselves earn little through taxes as they have reduced them to basically zero or at least to a miniscule rate.
Instead they use indirect taxation through the paying of fees and the support of a specialized work force which they can tax more.
In bona-fide tax havens which specialize in company, trust and foundation registration, yearly fees are required which make up for the lost revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that tax havens often sell out their sovereignty at the expense of their own citizens.
Many of them levy taxes on their citizens, while non-residents and their financial products are exempt from almost all taxes.
Instead, they make money by taxing the lawyers, accountants and other financial services professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, this is exactly a problem as tax havens rely disproportionally on a single industry which makes them increasingly susceptible to sudden changes in regulatory framework of other countries.
The poverty rate of Luxembourg has increased twofold as any redistributional policy is prevented on purpose.
The spoils of the offshore financial services industry thus accrue in the hands of a small and often non-resident work force while the main population suffers from the cuts in basic services and increasing house prices and costs of living.
The Crown Dependency of Jersey is another example where the local population is suffering disproportionately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The small size of most tax havens gives the local governments little to work with.
Would you build a huge production plant in a country with a demand of just 500.000 people?
In case of the Bahamas, the only thing they have beyond offshore financial services is sugar which is hardly a future proof or otherwise lucrative source of income for the country.
The small size also increases the probability that the country is ruled by an oligarchic or plutocratic elite which can utilize the proposed deregulation and offshoring as they make the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, offshore finance requires little capital as you only need a good internet or phone connection and a mailbox which can be claimed as a headquarter by 2.000 to 12.000 offshore companies.
Give or take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ### How to Combat Offshore Finance

HW p.92: Global Financial Registry

apportion taxes proportional to payroll, sales

## Globalized Finance

from 1950 to 1975 unusual long prosperity 4 to 4.6% (Glorieux Trenteuse in France) despite high tax rate TI77

2006 lower hourly wage of worker after inflation than 1970

1973 to 2000: 17 banking crises and 57 currency crises vs 16 before

US deregulation 1974 [?] --&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">It's all about regulatory arbitrage</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The British [Offshore] Empire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The British [Offshore] Empire" /><published>2022-04-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire/">&lt;p&gt;This summary delves deeper into the function and origin of the British offshore financial system which has played a pivotal role at creating the offshore financial industry which rests mostly on secrecy and illicit money streams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-city-of-london-part-1&quot;&gt;The City of London Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a small district right in the middle of London which is quite peculiar in its nature: the City of London.
Per se it is a simple local administration taking care of things every administration does: building roads and parks, making sure taxes are paid and providing other public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It traces its roots to Roman settlements and has continuously existed for close to 1000 years or more.
One thing the City of London is famous for is that it can claim to be the longest running municipal administration when King William gave the City of London the ‘William charter’ in 1067 establishing a basic rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time the City won more concessions from the British crown and was able to outlive queens, kings and wars by positioning itself as a center for trade and commerce.
Conspicuously enough, one stated objective of the City of London is to promote its financial services industry.
While most countries taciturnly agree on promoting their local industries, the City of London is interesting insofar that it’s government has put the promotion of its very own financial services industry right next to policing and the provision of other municipal services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-british-empire&quot;&gt;The British Empire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its height in 1913, the British empire held sway over 413 million people (23%) and 24% of land worldwide, although its dominions Australia and Canada, as well as India made up big chunks of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book ‘The Anarchy’ about the rise of the British East India Corporation (EIC), Charles Dalrymple mentions that the rise of the EIC was among other factors greatly facilitated by the superior financial system the British could muster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is commonly agreed upon that the splintering of the Indian monarchy was due to giving out taxation rights to subordinated generals and patrons, which by themselves were inherently not interested in passing on collected taxes to the Raj.
This in turn deprived the Raj of income with which he could tackle new projects and consolidate his power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the highly developed financial system mainly based in London was able to quickly move large amounts of money through the British sphere of influence.
Often battles were not even fought as opponents were simply bought off with large sums of cash or pivotal supporting army generals were paid to not show up at the side of their Indian allies by the British.
Similarly the British were well regarded by the local sepoys (Indian natives serving as soldiers) as paying salaries consistently on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enormous extent of the British empire gave the chaps back in London in the financial services sector a lot to do, since there were always bridges to be build, insurance contracts to be signed and loans to be made across the whole wide world under a single economic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London, and more specifically the City of London, thus developed to the most important financial center in the world under the auspice of the British empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we all know: All good things come to an end …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decline-of-the-british-empire&quot;&gt;Decline of the British Empire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having lost its role as the premier world power to the US after World War 2, Britain had a hard time adjusting to this new reality.
This was especially hard on the public school (public schools are the prestigious schools in the UK) educated generation that has and still forms the backbone of higher public office in the UK.
In half a generation, these mostly men watched their once great empire dissolving and their once proud status reduced to just another European power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Abdel Nasser nationalized the Suez canal, which was and still is of profound importance to world trade, the three countries of France, Britain and Israel decided on having Israel invade Egypt.
Under the pretense of keeping peace, the British and the French would then move in and bring back the Suez canal under European control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for conspiratorial countries, the US would have none of that.
General Abdel Nasser had certain sympathies for the socialist/communist cause and the US were afraid that the entire Arab cultural sphere would move closer to the Soviet Union which would have spelled doom on the West’s interest in Middle Eastern oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The escalating crisis and the dressing down of the UK caused a run on the Sterling.
The Bank of England (BoE) tried to support the Sterling but it ultimately cost it 450Mio USD which essentially bankrupted the BoE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a harsh new reality for the British chaps in their Savile Row suits as they had to recognize that the weren’t the biggest dog in the dog park anymore … still large but not the biggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of concern for the City of London was the capital control system introduced through the Bretton Woods system.
The two world wars had made the US the largest holder of Gold in the world which was quite something when all currencies had a fixed exchange rate to Gold.
(We now live in a world of fiat currencies, in which the value of almost every currency is determined on a sell-buy market through supply and demand.)
With the loans made to the UK (which passed those loans partially further along to France) during World War 1 and partially World War 2, the UK bought commodities and products from the US to keep on fighting the Germans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made the US the biggest player in the Gold market and after the complete or partial destruction of almost every other industrialized nation also the most important economy in the world (a title they still hold to this day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Bretton Woods in 1944 John Maynard Keynes proposed a global currency to conduct world wide trade but the US weren’t too keen on that idea as it undermined their powerful position as the worlds largest holder of Gold reserves which in turn gave them a large sway over international currency dynamics.
So the US dollar became the world reserve currency at 35 USD for one ounce of gold and every other currency could pick their peg with a some wiggle room of 1% around this peg for the central banks to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The memories of the global financial crisis of 1929 were just 15 years old and the crisis itself as well as WWII as a direct political consequence of too much speculation was still remembered vividly by the economists at Bretton Woods.
Thus they agreed on capital controls, sovereign monetary policy and fixed exchange rates to allows countries more autonomy in determining their economic course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These set of rules refers to the impossible trinity in macro economic circles which states that you can only have two of the following three: free capital flow, stable exchange rate and sovereign monetary policy.
With free capital flow and stable exchange rate, money sloshes in and out of your country and you have to set you macro economic agenda as country such that the exchange rate is stable despite the external influences, thus your macro economic policy has to tailored to accommodate the stable exchange rate.
With free capital flows and a sovereign economic policy you will keep pursuing your policy but the capital will flow in and out on a whim, reacting to your policy, so the exchange rate will fluctuate freely.
Finally with a stable exchange rate and a sovereign policy, you will have to control capital flows since otherwise you can’t keep the exchange rate fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key tool for central banks is the interest rate which banks can borrow money.
The rate is almost directly passed onto loans in the economy as the banks have to cover their cost of borrowing at the central bank by charging their costumers equivalently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s low, a lot of money will be borrowed with expands the money supply and hopefully stimulates the economy.
Conversely, freely moving money will leave the country because people will simply borrow at the low rates that the banks offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the interest rates are increased by a central bank, borrowing in that currency will be expensive for the banks which makes credit more expensive.
But if you have free cash somewhere on this planet, you can simply move that free money back to the country with the high interest rate and charge the corresponding high interest rate.
The trick is that you don’t have to borrow at the central bank compared to the local banks since you already have the money, so it’s a free gain.
This is the reason why emerging markets look at interest hikes of the Federal Reserve with trepidation, as ‘hot money’ aka freely investable money will be pulled from their economies and will be loaned out in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capital controls were very much to the detriment of the banks and more specifically London which relied on the free flow of capital across borders in a de-colonized world.
All international lending was suddenly put on hold as every international loan, which moved money from London to somewhere else on this planet, was restricted by tightly regulated in- and outflow of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The London banks which had been servicing all these different colonies in the British empire suddenly had little to do as money could only leave the country when it adhered to the capital controls set under the Bretton Woods system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-birth-of-euromarket&quot;&gt;The Birth of EuroMarket&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously annoyed the bankers of the once glorious British empire and there was a significant tug of war between the British treasury which followed the Bretton Woods system and the bankers who wanted those onerous regulations gone which inhibited them from lending to anyone they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here comes the first cultural quirk into play which enabled the birth of offshore finance.
The British banking system was a very tight knit group bred out of the elite private schools such as Eton.
The predominantly looked after the interests of their own to an extent that regulatory oversight was more or less having some tea once in a while and asking politely that you refrained from doing anything illegal.
This is a far cry from tough oversight in which people are punished if they went against the rules.
In this cozy atmosphere in which everybody knew everybody from their shared polo clubs, the interest lay largely in advancing the private clubs agenda which so happened to be geared towards international banking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact they were actively encouraging the circumvention of any stringent regulation as they missed the days of the great British empire and its influence on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this regulatory vacuum created from the old boys club, the EuroMarket was created.
The regulatory consensus by the BoE was basically, that it would adhere to Bretton Woods since it was pressured by the treasury and the government.
But fortunately, any currency beyond the Pound Sterling was technically not under their purview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things got really interesting once the Soviet Union stepped in.
Now just like any country, the Soviet Union held Dollar reserves to buy whatever they needed.
Remember that the USD was the world reserve currency which served as the currency of choice for international trade.
Sovereign countries were obviously exempt from the capital controls and held significant amounts of foreign currency reserves with the respective central banks to defend their currency pegs.
The USSR was legitimately concerned that their USD dollar reserves would be frozen by the US government once the Cold War turned from frosty to nuclear hot.
Therefore they kept their USD notes in Paris and London outside the reach of the US government with the Moscow Narodny Bank.
These were extraordinary amounts of foreign currencies which were beyond the control of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A medium sized bank called Midland bank started lending out these USD reserves and fortunately enough the BoE didn’t care as it wasn’t the Pound Sterling.
Rumor has it that the EuroMarket was named after the Euro telex address of the Moscow Narodny bank ML37, TI88, BW46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1960 the EuroMarket which were mostly USD sloshing outside the US was worth 1 Billion, ten years later in 1970 it was already 46 Billion USD.
In 1971 Nixon abolished the Gold standard which effectively initiated the decline of Bretton Woods.
Together with the shift towards a more neoliberal stance, capital control were revoked starting in 1973 and by 1979 effectively all capital controls were gone.
By 1980 the EuroMarket had thus ballooned to 500 Billion, and surging to 2.6 Trillion in 1988.
It should be noted that EuroMarket quickly came to encompass any freely movable currency besides the USD that one could think of.
So in 1997 the EuroMarket centered on London represented 90% of all international loans TI92.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;city-of-london-part-2&quot;&gt;City of London Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This free and ‘hot’ money coupled with the massive deregulation of the British financial markets in 1984 by Margaret Thatcher moved London finally back out of the shadow of New York City.
While NYC dominated the international markets in terms of securitization, London regained the pole position for international lending as the regulation was purposefully light-touch.
More interestingly, the City of London Corporation become solely focused on advancing the interests of the financial elite vis-a-vis its democratic function as an administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The City took the Citizen United idea of a legal person a step further and elevated corporations to voting members.
Due to its small size, the native population of the City of London is only 9.000 but it has 23.000 corporations registered in its business-friendly jurisdiction.
Each corporation has as many votes as it has employees but whereas democracy allows its voters to vote independently, the corporations bundle all votes of their employees.
Thus the population of the City of London may have democratic rights, but they are severely outvoted by the corporate interests.
Even more disturbing is that these corporations are allowed to vote in British elections.
This elevation of corporate and market interests above real people is a bonafide example of neoliberalism taken to its logical extreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly the City has three major cash funds which are used to pay for the smooth running of the day-to-day business of the City.
Most peculiar is the City Cash fund (TI268) about which is very little known except that it is the owner of many luxury buildings in London.
The City of London Corporation declines on disclosing how much money is in the City Cash Fund which implicitly signals that it would be huge.
Counterfactually, if the City Cash Fund would only contain 3-5 Mio Pounds, then it would be inconspicuous to disclose the paltry fund size.
Secondly as the fund works discreetly in the background it could be very well used as a political slush fund of sorts as there is no democratic oversight over its use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the EuroMarket and the Big Bang of 1984, the City of London has morphed into the hub of a hub-and-spoke system of offshore finance.
Small jurisdictions that are still parts of the British commonwealth have eagerly transformed themselves into offshore finance centers.
While the classic names are well known such as the Cayman islands and the Bahamas; Singapore, HongKong, the British Virgin Islands and also the Cook Islands have been busy as feeding pipelines of unregulated money into the City of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1/3 of all offshore wealth is in the spokes of this system whereas the entire system encompasses full 50% of all unaccounted money such as EuroDollars.
The Cayman Islands for example has over 80.000 companies, is the 5th largest financial center and has 3/4 of all hedge funds world wide … and it has one cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British were full on aware of the importance of their offshore system as the Crown Dependencies were adamantly defended from any intrusive regulation during the negations to join the European Union.
Dependencies such as the Isle of Guernsey, Isle of Jersey and other were vehemently defended from any possible regulation by the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="globalizedfinance" /><summary type="html">A Different Kind of Empire</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lebanon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6539&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6884&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7030&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7031&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7129-3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6230&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6231&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6241&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6242&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6306&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220331-_DSC6564&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220331-_DSC6659&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">Beirut and the Levant</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg" /></entry></feed>