<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-15T19:24:15+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ludwig Winkler</title><subtitle>Jekyll version of the Massively theme by HTML5UP</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The British [Offshore] Empire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The British [Offshore] Empire" /><published>2022-04-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/britishoffshoreempire/">&lt;p&gt;This summary delves deeper into the function and origin of the British offshore financial system which has played a pivotal role at creating the offshore financial industry which rests mostly on secrecy and illicit money streams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-city-of-london-part-1&quot;&gt;The City of London Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a small district right in the middle of London which is quite peculiar in its nature: the City of London.
Per se it is a simple local administration taking care of things every administration does: building roads and parks, making sure taxes are paid and providing other public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It traces its roots to Roman settlements and has continuously existed for close to 1000 years or more.
One thing the City of London is famous for is that it can claim to be the longest running municipal administration when King William gave the City of London the ‘William charter’ in 1067 establishing a basic rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time the City won more concessions from the British crown and was able to outlive queens, kings and wars by positioning itself as a center for trade and commerce.
Conspicuously enough, one stated objective of the City of London is to promote its financial services industry.
While most countries taciturnly agree on promoting their local industries, the City of London is interesting insofar that it’s government has put the promotion of its very own financial services industry right next to policing and the provision of other municipal services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-british-empire&quot;&gt;The British Empire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its height in 1913, the British empire held sway over 413 million people (23%) and 24% of land worldwide, although its dominions Australia and Canada, as well as India made up big chunks of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book ‘The Anarchy’ about the rise of the British East India Corporation (EIC), Charles Dalrymple mentions that the rise of the EIC was among other factors greatly facilitated by the superior financial system the British could muster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is commonly agreed upon that the splintering of the Indian monarchy was due to giving out taxation rights to subordinated generals and patrons, which by themselves were inherently not interested in passing on collected taxes to the Raj.
This in turn deprived the Raj of income with which he could tackle new projects and consolidate his power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the highly developed financial system mainly based in London was able to quickly move large amounts of money through the British sphere of influence.
Often battles were not even fought as opponents were simply bought off with large sums of cash or pivotal supporting army generals were paid to not show up at the side of their Indian allies by the British.
Similarly the British were well regarded by the local sepoys (Indian natives serving as soldiers) as paying salaries consistently on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enormous extent of the British empire gave the chaps back in London in the financial services sector a lot to do, since there were always bridges to be build, insurance contracts to be signed and loans to be made across the whole wide world under a single economic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London, and more specifically the City of London, thus developed to the most important financial center in the world under the auspice of the British empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we all know: All good things come to an end …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decline-of-the-british-empire&quot;&gt;Decline of the British Empire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having lost its role as the premier world power to the US after World War 2, Britain had a hard time adjusting to this new reality.
This was especially hard on the public school (public schools are the prestigious schools in the UK) educated generation that has and still forms the backbone of higher public office in the UK.
In half a generation, these mostly men watched their once great empire dissolving and their once proud status reduced to just another European power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Abdel Nasser nationalized the Suez canal, which was and still is of profound importance to world trade, the three countries of France, Britain and Israel decided on having Israel invade Egypt.
Under the pretense of keeping peace, the British and the French would then move in and bring back the Suez canal under European control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for conspiratorial countries, the US would have none of that.
General Abdel Nasser had certain sympathies for the socialist/communist cause and the US were afraid that the entire Arab cultural sphere would move closer to the Soviet Union which would have spelled doom on the West’s interest in Middle Eastern oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The escalating crisis and the dressing down of the UK caused a run on the Sterling.
The Bank of England (BoE) tried to support the Sterling but it ultimately cost it 450Mio USD which essentially bankrupted the BoE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a harsh new reality for the British chaps in their Savile Row suits as they had to recognize that the weren’t the biggest dog in the dog park anymore … still large but not the biggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of concern for the City of London was the capital control system introduced through the Bretton Woods system.
The two world wars had made the US the largest holder of Gold in the world which was quite something when all currencies had a fixed exchange rate to Gold.
(We now live in a world of fiat currencies, in which the value of almost every currency is determined on a sell-buy market through supply and demand.)
With the loans made to the UK (which passed those loans partially further along to France) during World War 1 and partially World War 2, the UK bought commodities and products from the US to keep on fighting the Germans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made the US the biggest player in the Gold market and after the complete or partial destruction of almost every other industrialized nation also the most important economy in the world (a title they still hold to this day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Bretton Woods in 1944 John Maynard Keynes proposed a global currency to conduct world wide trade but the US weren’t too keen on that idea as it undermined their powerful position as the worlds largest holder of Gold reserves which in turn gave them a large sway over international currency dynamics.
So the US dollar became the world reserve currency at 35 USD for one ounce of gold and every other currency could pick their peg with a some wiggle room of 1% around this peg for the central banks to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The memories of the global financial crisis of 1929 were just 15 years old and the crisis itself as well as WWII as a direct political consequence of too much speculation was still remembered vividly by the economists at Bretton Woods.
Thus they agreed on capital controls, sovereign monetary policy and fixed exchange rates to allows countries more autonomy in determining their economic course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These set of rules refers to the impossible trinity in macro economic circles which states that you can only have two of the following three: free capital flow, stable exchange rate and sovereign monetary policy.
With free capital flow and stable exchange rate, money sloshes in and out of your country and you have to set you macro economic agenda as country such that the exchange rate is stable despite the external influences, thus your macro economic policy has to tailored to accommodate the stable exchange rate.
With free capital flows and a sovereign economic policy you will keep pursuing your policy but the capital will flow in and out on a whim, reacting to your policy, so the exchange rate will fluctuate freely.
Finally with a stable exchange rate and a sovereign policy, you will have to control capital flows since otherwise you can’t keep the exchange rate fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key tool for central banks is the interest rate which banks can borrow money.
The rate is almost directly passed onto loans in the economy as the banks have to cover their cost of borrowing at the central bank by charging their costumers equivalently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s low, a lot of money will be borrowed with expands the money supply and hopefully stimulates the economy.
Conversely, freely moving money will leave the country because people will simply borrow at the low rates that the banks offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the interest rates are increased by a central bank, borrowing in that currency will be expensive for the banks which makes credit more expensive.
But if you have free cash somewhere on this planet, you can simply move that free money back to the country with the high interest rate and charge the corresponding high interest rate.
The trick is that you don’t have to borrow at the central bank compared to the local banks since you already have the money, so it’s a free gain.
This is the reason why emerging markets look at interest hikes of the Federal Reserve with trepidation, as ‘hot money’ aka freely investable money will be pulled from their economies and will be loaned out in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capital controls were very much to the detriment of the banks and more specifically London which relied on the free flow of capital across borders in a de-colonized world.
All international lending was suddenly put on hold as every international loan, which moved money from London to somewhere else on this planet, was restricted by tightly regulated in- and outflow of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The London banks which had been servicing all these different colonies in the British empire suddenly had little to do as money could only leave the country when it adhered to the capital controls set under the Bretton Woods system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-birth-of-euromarket&quot;&gt;The Birth of EuroMarket&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously annoyed the bankers of the once glorious British empire and there was a significant tug of war between the British treasury which followed the Bretton Woods system and the bankers who wanted those onerous regulations gone which inhibited them from lending to anyone they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here comes the first cultural quirk into play which enabled the birth of offshore finance.
The British banking system was a very tight knit group bred out of the elite private schools such as Eton.
The predominantly looked after the interests of their own to an extent that regulatory oversight was more or less having some tea once in a while and asking politely that you refrained from doing anything illegal.
This is a far cry from tough oversight in which people are punished if they went against the rules.
In this cozy atmosphere in which everybody knew everybody from their shared polo clubs, the interest lay largely in advancing the private clubs agenda which so happened to be geared towards international banking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact they were actively encouraging the circumvention of any stringent regulation as they missed the days of the great British empire and its influence on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this regulatory vacuum created from the old boys club, the EuroMarket was created.
The regulatory consensus by the BoE was basically, that it would adhere to Bretton Woods since it was pressured by the treasury and the government.
But fortunately, any currency beyond the Pound Sterling was technically not under their purview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things got really interesting once the Soviet Union stepped in.
Now just like any country, the Soviet Union held Dollar reserves to buy whatever they needed.
Remember that the USD was the world reserve currency which served as the currency of choice for international trade.
Sovereign countries were obviously exempt from the capital controls and held significant amounts of foreign currency reserves with the respective central banks to defend their currency pegs.
The USSR was legitimately concerned that their USD dollar reserves would be frozen by the US government once the Cold War turned from frosty to nuclear hot.
Therefore they kept their USD notes in Paris and London outside the reach of the US government with the Moscow Narodny Bank.
These were extraordinary amounts of foreign currencies which were beyond the control of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A medium sized bank called Midland bank started lending out these USD reserves and fortunately enough the BoE didn’t care as it wasn’t the Pound Sterling.
Rumor has it that the EuroMarket was named after the Euro telex address of the Moscow Narodny bank ML37, TI88, BW46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1960 the EuroMarket which were mostly USD sloshing outside the US was worth 1 Billion, ten years later in 1970 it was already 46 Billion USD.
In 1971 Nixon abolished the Gold standard which effectively initiated the decline of Bretton Woods.
Together with the shift towards a more neoliberal stance, capital control were revoked starting in 1973 and by 1979 effectively all capital controls were gone.
By 1980 the EuroMarket had thus ballooned to 500 Billion, and surging to 2.6 Trillion in 1988.
It should be noted that EuroMarket quickly came to encompass any freely movable currency besides the USD that one could think of.
So in 1997 the EuroMarket centered on London represented 90% of all international loans TI92.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;city-of-london-part-2&quot;&gt;City of London Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This free and ‘hot’ money coupled with the massive deregulation of the British financial markets in 1984 by Margaret Thatcher moved London finally back out of the shadow of New York City.
While NYC dominated the international markets in terms of securitization, London regained the pole position for international lending as the regulation was purposefully light-touch.
More interestingly, the City of London Corporation become solely focused on advancing the interests of the financial elite vis-a-vis its democratic function as an administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The City took the Citizen United idea of a legal person a step further and elevated corporations to voting members.
Due to its small size, the native population of the City of London is only 9.000 but it has 23.000 corporations registered in its business-friendly jurisdiction.
Each corporation has as many votes as it has employees but whereas democracy allows its voters to vote independently, the corporations bundle all votes of their employees.
Thus the population of the City of London may have democratic rights, but they are severely outvoted by the corporate interests.
Even more disturbing is that these corporations are allowed to vote in British elections.
This elevation of corporate and market interests above real people is a bonafide example of neoliberalism taken to its logical extreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly the City has three major cash funds which are used to pay for the smooth running of the day-to-day business of the City.
Most peculiar is the City Cash fund (TI268) about which is very little known except that it is the owner of many luxury buildings in London.
The City of London Corporation declines on disclosing how much money is in the City Cash Fund which implicitly signals that it would be huge.
Counterfactually, if the City Cash Fund would only contain 3-5 Mio Pounds, then it would be inconspicuous to disclose the paltry fund size.
Secondly as the fund works discreetly in the background it could be very well used as a political slush fund of sorts as there is no democratic oversight over its use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the EuroMarket and the Big Bang of 1984, the City of London has morphed into the hub of a hub-and-spoke system of offshore finance.
Small jurisdictions that are still parts of the British commonwealth have eagerly transformed themselves into offshore finance centers.
While the classic names are well known such as the Cayman islands and the Bahamas; Singapore, HongKong, the British Virgin Islands and also the Cook Islands have been busy as Feeding pipelines of unregulated money into the City of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that 1/3 of all offshore wealth is in the spokes of this system whereas the entire system encompasses full 50% of all unaccounted money such as EuroDollars.
The Cayman Islands for example has over 80.000 companies, is the 5th largest financial center and has 3/4 of all hedge funds world wide … and it has one cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British were full on aware of the importance of their offshore system as the Crown Dependencies were adamantly defended from any intrusive regulation during the negations to join the European Union.
Dependencies such as the Isle of Guernsey, Isle of Jersey and other were vehemently defended from any possible regulation by the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="otherblog" /><summary type="html">A Different Kind of Empire</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lebanon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lebanon2022/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6342-Enhanced.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6539&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6539&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6782-Pano&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6782-Pano.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC6884&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC6884&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6884.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7030&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7030&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7030.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7031&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7031&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot; title=&quot;20220327-_DSC7129-3&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220327-_DSC7129-3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC7129-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6230&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6230&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6230.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6231&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6231&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6231.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6241&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6241&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6241.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6242&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6242&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6242.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot; title=&quot;20220328-_DSC6306&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220328-_DSC6306&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220328-_DSC6306.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6564&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220331-_DSC6564&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6564.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot; title=&quot;20220331-_DSC6659&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;20220331-_DSC6659&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220331-_DSC6659.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/lebanon22/20220327-_DSC6539.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Off-Shore Finance Centers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Off-Shore Finance Centers" /><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinancecenters/">&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the Tax Justice Network published a ground breaking &lt;a href=&quot;https://fsi.taxjustice.net&quot;&gt;ranking&lt;/a&gt; which evaluated countries on how much financial secrecy they provided to somebody who wanted to move their money and wealth undisturbed across the world and free from democratic and/or governmental oversight.
The biggest surprise back then was the country on top of the list, while the succeeding ranks were populated by the usual suspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2008, the list has changed a bit as for example Singapore has moved up significantly.
The reason for that is that it fulfills the little hinterland requirement, a strong rule of law and a good integration into the global economy.
Especially Swiss banks are preparing for a stricter financial secrecy regulation in Europe and the US, and have picked Singapore with even stricter bank secrecy laws as their contingency jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurpringly, the usual suspects were present in the Tax Justice Network Financial Secrecy Ranking but the number one spot might surprise you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Cayman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Switzerland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Luxembourg&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) US&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, how did US come out on top?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s go through the list step by step …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uk&quot;&gt;UK&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an entire blog post dedicated to the rise of the British offshore system.
Arguably, the British were the midwifes of the offshore financial system through the City of London.
The offshore and EuroMarket system would have probably developed any way as the interests of the financial sector for less regulation and oversight are are found in every country.
It just so happened that the UK was the birthplace due to its strongly developed financial services industry from times of the mighty British empire and its especially lax regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British offshore system is organized in a hub-and-spoke system where the City of London sits in the middle.
It represents the spider in a world wide spiders web that serve as conduit of clandestine money.
A full 1/3 of all offshore wealth is deposited in the former colonies and Crown dependencies of the UK.
Add the City of London to it and the a full 1/2 of all offshore wealth is domiciled in the former British empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, while the British themselves on their rainy island were busy creating the EuroMarket, the Caribbean offshore industry was developed in close cooperation with American lawyers and accountants.
This was mainly due to the close proximity of the US to the pleasant weather which made a quick deposit of secret money in your favorite Caribbean bank account pleasant and convenient.
In fact the first shell company legislation was written on the British Virgin Islands by an American lawyer, the BVI’s DUDE HAVE TO LOOK UP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;switzerland&quot;&gt;Switzerland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Schweizerische Eidgenossenschaft’ has constructed its entire political identity around the notion of neutrality, grass-roots democracy and non-interference.
It thus serves as international neutral ground on which many global organizations have their headquarters and provides services typical of an entrepot or international conduit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swiss federation has put increased emphasis on local governments of the 26 cantons to administer their communities according to their liking.
This follows the Swiss idea of direct democracy in which many issues are decided upon through referendums.
This direct democracy was the reason why the Swiss federation agreed only in 1971 to grant women the voting right.
But it would take another 20 years to 1991 for the last canton Appenzell Innerrhoden to fully implement female suffrage following a law suit by women from this canton.
This was a direct outgrowth of the independent, localized legislation that is a hallmark of Swiss political identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switzerland’s neutrality was guaranteed at the Congress of Vienna, where the aristocracy of Europe redistributed the continent among themselves after the civil revolution originating from the French revolution in 1792.
The formalization of Swiss neutrality induced an influx of capital where the Italians banked in Lugano, the French in Geneva and the Germans in Zurich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The huge financial burden of World War I led to a ten fold increase, as all belligerent countries raised taxes during and after the war.
From 1920 to 1929, the annual growth was 14% which coinceded with the 1920-21 and 1925-27 French tax increases.
Following the world financial crisis in 1929, the annual growth fell to only 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the World Financial Crisis 1929, the lower and middle class populace of Switzerland was rightfully so angry at the banks for as they were made responsible for the repercussions felt by the population.
While banking secrecy had already existed in Switzerland, it had merely been encoded in the civil law, meaning that the state wouldn’t prosecute it.
With the increased scrutiny by the Swiss public towards their dealings, the banking and business circles wanted to make sure that the Swiss state wouldn’t get any supervisional rights.
What was even worse to them, was that the supervision could include some sort of privy into the bank-client relationship.
THus they enforced the banking secrecy legislation in the criminal law.
The drafting of the law started in 1933 whereas the idea of stricter regulation started as early as 1931.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that occured as a direct consequence of the financial crisis 1929 and the subsequent public outrage resulting in the passage of the law in 1934.
This stands in direct opposition to the idea that Swiss bank secrecy was enshrined to protect the wealth of Jews from the Nazis which is honestly a lie by the Swiss public opinion.
The were just as anti-semitic as everybody else in Europe and even made Swiss jews pay for the costs of taking on Jews flewing from the Nazis and seeking refuge in Switzerland.
From 1933 to 1945, only 1.5% of all new accounts were in fact Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Switzerland became an international point of attraction for flight capital due to its favourable financial conditions, the cantons inside Switzerland competed for the flight capital just the way Switzerland competed on an international stage.
Remember that each canton in Switzerland has a fair amount of leeway on what kind of laws it wants to pass.
Thus the cantons started a race to the bottom, undercutting each other in the hopes of attracting more of the money flowing into Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the canton of Zug hosts 27.000 corporations: 4 for every one of its inhabitants.
The extreme imbalance of hidden wealth to people results in another intersting statistic: although the Swiss population comprises only 0.1% of the world population, a full 1/3 of American stock market is held by Swiss banks for its costumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When money flows into a country, it is idealistically converted to the local currency when it crosses the border.
This generates a demand for the local currency.
In Switzerland’s case this in fact changed the sign of the interest rate banks charge you for taking your money.
Normally, banks are happy to store your money as it gives them capital to lend it out at a higher rate.
But in Switzerlands case the central bank of Switzerland started to charge -0.75% for all banks lending money from them, starting from 2015.
By 2022 they reduced it to -0.25% as the interest in the Swiss franc as a stable safe haven waned.
But it will probably increase again as spectre of inflation haunts all of the major currencies.
A nice side effect implemented by the Swiss banks is that the negative interest rates are only applied to savings account such that customers are encouraged to move their wealth to the wealth management division.
But obviously that’s only viable for rich people, so the poor loose out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;luxembourg&quot;&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grand Duchy has paralyzed the EU’s fight against offshore finance like a very active sleeper agent in the center of Europe between Germany and France.
It was a founding member of the European Union at the Treaty of Rome in 1957.
But since then, it has changed dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that Luxembourg does not owe its success in offshore finance to its so-called stability or highly skilled workforce.
What is has to offer as its modern history is a story of a regulatory capture and the cautionary tale of an entrenched elite.
The royal family has maintained on the throne since 1783 which is impressive given the tumultuous centuries thereafter.
More importantly the Christian Social Peoples Party has provided the prime minister since WWII except for five years in the 1970’s and after the election of 2013.
This is similar to the Isle of Jersey in which the ruling elite has created a micro-cosmos in which everybody knows everybody and anybody not toeing the plutocratic line is ostracized immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does owe its success in international finance to its utter selling out of its sovereignty to the highest bidder.
In the 1970s, this little state of 500.000 people started selling a truely new product to multinational companies: the explicit offer to let them choose their own taxation, regulatory constraints and legal obligations.
Does a big international bank want to set up a new multi-billion fund?
Let them decide their own tax rate, effectively 0% on profits. Nice.
Does the same bank want to sell securities to raise cash and satisfy the capital requirements of another country’s regulators?
Let the bank create their own ‘hybrid securities’ which act as securities to regulators and as debt to the tax department, thus making their profits deductible from the corporate income tax. Convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation and servicing of the holding structures, shell companies and multinational registration requires a significant workforce.
In Luxembourg, 150.000 people commute every day from France, Belgium and Germany into the Grand Duchy with a population of a mere 500.000.
This greatly distorts macro economic statistics, as the gross domestic product is only 2/3 of the gross national product, after subtracting the wages paid to the commuting workforce from the neighboring countries and the dividends and interest to the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anybody arguing that hypertropic financial sectors lift all economic boats in a country should look at Luxembourg.
GDP per worker has grown only 1.4% per year, which was essentially wiped out by inflation every year.
Salaries in the offshore finance industry and business consulting have exploded, implicitly at the cost of other countries tax revenue, while manufacturing, transportation and construction workers have not seen any real wage increase in twenty years.
Luxembourg has essentially pushed its lower class into the neighboring countries which now commute to work from France, Germany and Belgium as well.
The poverty in Luxembourg has doubled since 1980 as all the tax cuts to the cheapest bidder have impacted basically everybody not working in offshore finance.
The tax cutes and externalization of its work force has left the educational system in shambles as Luxembourg performs among the worst in the OECD club and scholastic inequality is among the highest.
Housing prices have tripled in a country with little to show for except a castle and Luxembourg city is now as expensive as London which mops the floor with Luxembourg City in terms of basic attractions of an interesting city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why hasn’t the EU done anything about a brazen offshore centre in its middle which has sold its sovereignty to the cheapest bidder while enjoying and living off the advantage of the European Union?
A birth defect of the EU is that every member obtains a veto right which allows Luxembourg to torpedo any advance in combating offshore finance in the EU itself.
With the secret meetings of the European Council, a plutocratic prime minister of a country with a bare 500.000 inhabitants and with little to show for in terms of a genuine economy can dictate terms on the 500 million people of the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;usa&quot;&gt;USA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the United States have become the most accommodating country to money which likes to move around the world in the shadows.
Three main reasons stand out in the US top rank in the Financial Secrecy Index: the federalist political structure, its pro-business, deregulated environment after neoliberalism became a bon-mot in the 1980’s and the therefrom originating power of Wall Street over Washington DC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1981, it was becoming evident that the advance of the unregulated EuroMarket couldn’t be stopped.
US banks had already overrun London with local branches and had quickly become the major players in the London EuroMarket.
So instead of trying to fight it, US regulators started to imitate it with International Banking Facilities (IBF).
Similar to offshore banking in London, IBFs exist in the physical offices of US banks, but everything is separated from the US operations books.
Thus the banks have to set of books on the same desk: one for the US operations and one for the unregulated offshore market.
IBFs can offer deposit and loan services only to non-US residents and institutions.
More importantly, the offshore books are free of the reserve requirements of the US Federal Reserve and thus generate more profit.
The IBF’s were proposed in 1978 in a direct attempt to stem the flow of money from the US into the offshore market.
The Japanese quickly followed with the Japanese Offshore Markets (JOM) and thus the three big financial centers of the world all embraced the unregulated offshore market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The states of Delaware, Wyoming, South Dakota and Nevada have worked hard to be as welcoming as possible to money, the origin of which nobody should know of.
It all started with Delaware, which is small, yet unremarkable state in search of a new source of revenue.
The chemical giant DuPont basically ruled over Delaware from its headquarters in the capital of Wilmington.
Thus a very large company resided in the a very small state which gave the big corporation significant sway through its sheer size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the economy become sluggish in the 1980’s, a deregulation of interest rates was proposed to attract banking business.
In fact, the backers of a new deregulation bill on interest rate caps sought to emulate Luxembourg and become its version in the United States.
Very quickly, the big banks noticed the removed restriction on interest rates and rushed into the state.
South Dakota did something similar and removed its usury laws with a statute which was basically written by CitiBank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of Delaware quickly realized how much business it could attract given its inconspicuous size, if allowed companies more leeway and deregulated basically all restrictions away.
They quickly hopped onto the shell company wagon as they observed the rise of the Caribbean offshore financial centers.
With talks ramping up in the 1980’s between the UK and China on the repatriation of Hong Kong, Delaware trade delegations heavily courted the Hong Kong.
This is a somewhat amusing story since the number 8 is considered lucky in Chinese culture and Delaware beat the drum for incorporating Chinese holding companies on August 8, 1988.
But the British Virgin Islands did the same thing by keeping offices open on its Emancipation Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas the infamous Ugland hous in the Cayman Islands holds 12.000 corporations, one office in Delaware alone holds 217.000 companies.
In fact, Delaware is so popular, that 1209 North Orange Street is in the legal sense the home of Ford, GM, Coca-Cola, KFC, Intel, Google, HP and Texas Instruments all managed by Corporation Trust, a subsidiary of the Dutch Firm Wolters-Kluwer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 80’s, Delaware has risen to the preeminent location of anonymous shell companies in the US.
Wyoming, South Dakota and Nevada have quickly followed suit by facilitating the creation of companies and requiring little to no information on the incorporation of companies.
In fact Nevada does not even share tax or incorporation information the the federal state allowing the formation of, for all intents and purposes, secret companies right in the middle of the United States.
South Dakota has specialized in trusts and literally does not share information on trusts formed within its state boundaries.
So essentially, one could create a trust, accumulate enormous sums of money in that trust and nobody would actually know about it.
Imagine a, for example, five billion USD heavy trust under the control of an unknown person and whose existence is not known to the public.
The problem is in fact that nobody knows how much money resides in South Dakota trusts, as they are per law shrouded in secrecy.
Nevada and Wyoming require no identification documents on who the principal owner of a shell corporation is.
For the company director, you can simply pay anybody 20 USD to put their name on the filings and you got your company.
When you search for company formation agents in Nevada and the like you usually get prices starting at 249 depending on the type of corporate entity you want to have.
For 249 USD you get a company, add another 150 USD for a Nevada nominee officer and your name disappears from the registration thus giving you a perfect anonymous shell company.
For 949 USD you get the premium package and get an anonymous shell company equipped with a bank account.
Thus you can start your shady dealings right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then take that anonymous company and open a bank account at your local bank and start transferring money into the United States.
With that money you can buy luxury real estate or super expensive cars to park you money or sell it again later to get money from a valid transaction instead of for example selling cocaine.
Thus these companies are used to launder dirty money right in the United States.
If the authorities come knocking on your door, they have no way to know who really controls the shell company that you used to launder the money.
It could be Kim Jong-Un’s dictatorship, the LosZetas cartel from Mexico or the Iranian Revolutionary Guard.
You literally can’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now obviously it’s a bit suspicious if a company gets incorporated and immediately starts dealing with eight to nine figure transactions.
This is why incorporation agents in Delaware, Nevada and Wyoming offer aged or shelved companies which give of a more serious vibe through having existed at least on paper for multiple years.
These are usefull for fraud, as people tend to believe that companies that are multiple years old must have a somewhat reliable business model.
Yet again these are pure shell companies but you can have one for only 299 USD.
Who said money laundering has to be expensive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="otherblog" /><summary type="html">Drinking a Pina Colada and getting wet[&amp;rich] in the rain</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Off-Shore Finance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Off-Shore Finance" /><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/offshorefinance/">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt; MathJax.Hub.Config({ TeX: { equationNumbers: { autoNumber: &quot;all&quot; } } }); &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt;
         MathJax.Hub.Config({
           tex2jax: {
             inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], [&quot;\\(&quot;,&quot;\\)&quot;] ],
             displayMath: [['$$','$$']],
             processEscapes: true
           }
         });
       &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;origins&quot;&gt;Origins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Second World War was entering its final stage as the attendees of the Bretton Woods conference convened to determine the post war financial order of the world.
The influx of money into the United States due to World War I and the loans of the yet unfinished World War 2 made the US hold close to half of all gold reserves world wide.
This made them yield considerable power money wise entering the negotiations in a world in which all currencies had a gold peg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the impossible trinity (pick two out of three) of stable exchange rates, economic sovereignty and free capital, the representatives of the attending nations decided to impose capital controls on its citizens in favour of stable currencies and macro-economic sovereignty.
This essentially restricted banks to only do business in their respective countries as money could not leave a country on a whim or at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a severe blow to the bankers in the City of London which had been accustomed to banking in the economic sphere of the British empire.
It put the City of London into a comatose state as there wasn’t enough business to do for the banks which had previously serviced the financial needs in an empire encompassing close to a quarter of the worlds populations at its peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the British banking establishment, the Bank of England was more supporter than regulator as everybody knew everybody else in the upper echelons of British society.
The attendance of exclusive private schools and the shared reminiscence of the might of the British empire instilled a sense of entitlement that the internationally agreed upon laws did not apply to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus when the USD from the Soviet foreign banks started to being lent out by British banks, the British regulators were happy that international banking had returned to England.
These dollars that circulated outside the control of the Federal Reserve that was responsible for them were called EuroDollars.
In 1963 the first EuroBonds were sold which were unregulated bearer bonds.
Now bearer bonds are the perfect tool for tax evasion and money laundering.
Essentially the are like an ultra valuable dollar bill with a worth of whatever the issuer thinks fits his needs.
No record is kept of their purchase or sale as they are unregulated.
Thus you can buy them in one part of the onshore financial system, cross any border you want with the piece of ultra valuable unregulated paper, and sell it somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money for the exploding EuroBonds market came from all the hidden money stashed away in the Swiss bank vaults.
If you have money in numbered bank accounts in Switzerland you’re definitely happy that your money is safe.
But at the same it could be working for you, being lent out to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The German banker Siegmund Warburg and Scottish war hero Ian Fraser organized a quite dizzying setup to ensure that the bonds they were issuing skirted around every possible regulation and went through every imaginable loop hole.
Often these financial products used different quirks in different European countries to their advantage to remain as unregulated as possible, something called regulatory arbitrage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first EuroBonds by Siegmund Warburg were formally issued in Schiphol airport in the Netherlands.
They paid their interest in Luxembourg, free of charge.
They were listed on the London Stock Exchange.
And the borrower was officially the Italian Autostrade, an Italian state motorway company, while it was in fact the Italian IRI state holding company.
All while being a bearer bond as it was registered and regulated nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there the EuroMarkets exploded in all directions right under the pathetic nose of the Bank of England which was actively doing nothing, happy that business was flowing again in London.
Business, which economists and politicians had prudently and wisely restricted through capital controls to shield the real economy from financial crashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1960 the EuroMarket which were mostly USD sloshing outside the US was worth 1 Billion, ten years later in 1970 it was already 46 Billion USD.
In 1971 Nixon abolished the Gold standard which effectively initiated the decline of Bretton Woods.
Together with the shift towards a more neoliberal stance, capital control were revoked starting in 1973 and by 1979 effectively all capital controls were gone.
By 1980 the EuroMarket had thus ballooned to 500 Billion, and surging to 2.6 Trillion in 1988.
It should be noted that EuroMarket quickly came to encompass any freely movable currency besides the USD that one could think of.
So in 1997 the EuroMarket centered on London represented 90% of all international loans TI92.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wealth-in-off-shore-finance-system&quot;&gt;Wealth in Off Shore Finance System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to estimate the amount of wealth that is stored in the offshore financial center as the purpose of offshore is to remain hidden and untraceable.
Gabriel Zucman estimates it to be around 8% of all wealth.
The way he proceeds is to analyze the liabilities-holdings gap when comparing international statistical data on wealth.
If you had a secret bank account you would most likely want your money to do something, like be invested in stocks.
It turns out that 1/3 of the American stock market is held by Swiss bank accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume a British person has hid wealth in Switzerland and tasked his Swiss bank to buy stocks in the US.
American statisticians see is that American stock is held by foreigners, which is marked as a liability.
In Switzerland nothing is recorded, as the bank is merely holding the stocks not owning them.
In the UK, no assets are recorded as the British persons wants his stock ownership to be kept secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now normally the assets and liabilities should cancel each other out, as something being owned by a foreigner in one country should pop up as the property of that foreigner in his home country.
But there is a massive hole valued at 7.6 trillion USD which represents 8% of the global wealth which is unaccounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is Luxembourg as the second largest incorporater of mutual funds.
The regulators in Luxembourg say that 3.5 trillion USD are owned via shares in Luxembourg.
But when you scour the statistics worldwide, one can only find 1.5 trillion USD officially registered in Luxembourg which means that 2 trillion USD are unaccounted for, held by people who do not want to claim their ownership of mutual fund shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;secrecy-jursidictions&quot;&gt;Secrecy Jursidictions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people think about offshore finance and tax havens, they usually think of rich people not wanting to pay taxes.
This is most certainly true but above all these offshore financial centers are secrecy jurisdictions, in which nobody knows whats actually happening.
A side effect is that if you don’t know that somebody parked his or her wealth somewhere, then you also can’t tax it.
Another big draw for offshore centers is their prevalent deregulation, to the point of regulatory castration, in a laissez-faire approach to economics with which most economic historians will strongly disagree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way the rich, powerful, crooked or greedy (or any combination thereof) like to secure, hide and defend their wealth is through three main tools: trusts in the Anglo-Saxon sphere, foundations and shell companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trusts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trusts are a patriarchic quirk of British law dating back to the dark ages.
Back then, when a men went on the crusades, he obvious wasn’t home to defend his estate and property.
And because women weren’t allowed to hold land, he signed his property over to a friend who remained back in England.
The crusader would be the trust settlor, the friend staying in England the trustee and the wife and kids of the crusader were the beneficiaries.
Thus the ownership was signed over to the trustee with the clear purpose that the trustee manage the property and assets in a way to benefit the beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, trusts have lost their patriarchic purpose but now serve the nefarious purpose of hiding and defending secret wealth.
The main purpose of a trust in our time is to protect wealth from taxation, regulators and creditors.
They are created through the legal fiction of separating ownership from control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that reason they are for example very popular with rich Muslims.
Islams declares having a mortgage and an insurance policy haram, as planning out for the future goes against Allah’s divine plan and him taking care of you as a pious Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides cultural sensibilities, the sparsity of law and regulation make trusts very popular for wealth management.
They are not taxed as entities, but are taxed were the trustee is registered.
In a peculiar twist, offshore financial centers offer 0% tax rate on trusts and consequentially on trustees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the trustee is the legally liable person of the assets parked in the trust, creditors and regulators who might be after the trust settlors assets can’t touch the assets as the settlor has ceded ownership to the trustee.
And if you want to really cautious, you can insert the OFC speciality of ‘flee clauses’ into a trust agreement.
Should anybody come knocking on a trustee’s door or should more favourable terms be viable elsewhere, the trust can change legal registration in the blink of an eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English law foresaw the a restriction on perpetuity, as they did not want assets accumulating in trusts.
Over time, these accumulating assets could possibly give the trust structure outsized economic might and increase social inequality.
Thus they were limited to 99 years to prevent economic dynasties.
Guess what the offshore centers did: they abolished these rules.
But Wyoming and South Dakota did the same thing, so it’s not only the Brits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal advantage of trusts is that the law defines trust as ‘a fidicuary relationship with respect to property’.
Importantly, such a relationship can be defined in any way possible, allowing for multitudes of special arrangement.
But even more importantly, the beneficiaries and the trust itself is nowhere recorded.
So you can theoretically move 5 billion USD into an offshore trust, name your kids the beneficiaries and the tax men wouldn’t even know.
This obscurity and outright secrecy makes trusts so appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time there is the thorny issue of the trustee which you have to pick carefully.
When offshore centers tried to vie for Asian ultra hight net worth (UHNW) individuals, they quickly realized that Asian mostly patriarchs were loath relinquishing control over their companies to a trustee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the British Virgin Islands VISTA structures were developed.
The Virgin Islands Special Trust Act removed any duties, obligations and liabilities from the trustee.
See, normally the trustee is liable for the successful managing of the assets put into the trust.
This includes running an entire company, if the settlor so chose to park an entire company in the trust.
With VISTA, the trustee only role is to be a placeholder for the owner of the company, while it is run by the settlor.
Another innovation, if you want to call it that, was the creation of the protector role which allows the protector chosen by the settlor to remove and reassign trustee roles.
While not really necessary for wealth managers of UHNWI’s as they are usually professionals, it does give more power to the settlor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cayman Islands Special Trust Alternative Regime (STAR) innovated by removing the constraint of having people being the sole beneficiaries of a trust.
STAR trusts expanded the purpose of a trust to literally anything, increasing the beneficiaries wealth or even political goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foundations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundations are popular for a similar reasons as VISTA and STAR trusts as they give the creator a lot of leeway.
They are predominantly used by rich people from BRICS countries, where wealth generation has been immense, but the formation of general trust not so much.
Similar to Asian rich people from low trust countries, they also loath the idea of relinquishing control to strangers.
But with foundations, the founder has signatory authority on the foundations bank accounts, giving him full control.
For example, Panama has developed itself into the center for Latin American wealth management, as Latin Americans have experience much political unrest and have high force inheritance laws.
Thus they want to protect their wealth without ceding control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Merriam-Webster dictionary, a foundation is ‘funds given for the permanent support of an institution’ or ‘an organization or institution established by endowment with provision for future maintenance’.
Funnily enough, the definition goes on citing directly an offshore wealth management technique by naming ‘a trust administered by a foundation’ as an example.
While most people attribute philanthropic ideals to a foundation, by law it is just assets and money given for the support of a specific cause for future generations.
So in reality the purpose of a foundation can be anything the founder wants it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big advantage of foundations in terms of maintaining control is that the founder can be both beneficiary of the foundation and be the director of the council of the foundation.
Coupled with the signatory authority, the founder can have maximum control over what happens with and inside of a foundation.
Also assets can be moved in and out of a foundation, making it a flexible asset protection structure.
Additionally, a foundation can open bank accounts and go into contracts.
Compared to trusts which are a British common law structure and aren’t recognized by civil law, foundations are universally accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside compared to trusts is that they have to registered as a legal person, making them more visible than trusts.
But Panama and the Seychelles already offer foundations with nominee founders such that the names of the real founders are in the dark again.
Due to the public registration, administrative costs of foundations are higher, as bylaws and articles have to be formulated and they are usually audited.
Also, transferring wealth into foundations can be taxed in most onshore countries and as a legal person a foundation cna be sued and go bankrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shell Companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to trusts, which are only recognized in common law countries, and foundations which have to hold up to public/governmental scrutiny, companies are universally recognized legal entities.
Similarly to foundations they can exist in perpetuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US have vigorously defended their spot on the top of the Financial Secrecy Index, they can be had for as little as 250 USD in states like Nevada, Wyoming and Delaware.
In the more advanced secrecy jurisdictions they come with the extra flavour of nominee directors, which keep the beneficial owner’s name off the records.
For the registration, these secrecy jurisdictions don’t require identification, but the company does require directors.
So the nominee directors serve as as directors for a the shell company while doing absolutely nothing in terms of real managing of the company.
There is a story of a 23 year old fast food cook who was the nominee director of a New Zealand company.
The 20 USD he was paid were quite nice until international prosecutors knocked on his door, asking him why he was the director of an arms smuggling company.
It turned out that the company he had been a nominee director of had been involved in arms trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage is that companies can open bank accounts and that credit cards can be given out on those accounts.
Barclays, a British bank, had to admit, that close to 19% of its credit cards were linked to bank accounts in tax havens registered to shell companies.
Thus, presumably, the beneficial owners moved their wealth into tax havens, set up a shell company with a bank account, and then used a credit card on the shell company’s bank account to go shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some jurisdictions even offer bearer shares which is a stupendous money laundering tool.
The transactions of bearer shares are recorded nowhere and the person who is the bearer of the share is the owner of it.
But legally, the owner of those bearer shares can under oath say that as long as he’s not physically holding the share in his hand, that he’s not the owner of the company.
So imagine a company laundering money and the police comes asking the supposed owner of the company, who’s exerting control over the company via bearer shares, whether he owns the company or not.
Then the owner, who’s doing money laundering, can say ‘No’ and thats legally valid.
Offshore is a weird world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, shell companies are hid behind the lawyer-client privilege as a lawyer is used as the front man.
This adds another lawyer of obfuscation since the name of the true owner of a shell company can’t be divulged by force.
Thus if the police comes knocking, the lawyer is protected from having to name the true owner of the company as it would violate the lawyer-client confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, wealth and companies are place in a trust-company structure.
The company allows maximum flexibility and access to the parked wealth by offering credit cards and being able to move assets in and out of the company.
The shares of the company are then put into a trust with a nominee.
Thus the owner of the wealth and onshore corporation can do whatever he or she wants.
But in case the tax authority wants to inquire who all this wealth belongs to, the trust arrangement separates legally separates the settlor from is assets.
Similarly, creditors can’t access the company assets as they belong to the trust and no the settlor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Limited Liability Partnerships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your business interests can also be incorporated into a Limited Liability Partnership which are ‘tax transparent’.
First of all, partnerships are subject to far less scrutiny than real companies, as only the partners have money in them.
Thus only the partners money is involved and not the publics.
Stock companies are more transparent as the public can invest in them so they are held to more stringent standards.
Thus partnerships are in general more opaque has nobody but the partners have their money in them.
But traditionally, partners were also on the hook should something go awry.
Also, partnerships are taxed on a per partner basis, such that any profits or losses the partnerships accrues is passed directly onto the partners.
Thus profits and losses are directly taxed with the individual partners, making the tax transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited Liability Partnerships (LLP) were created on behest of the big four accounting firms on the Isle of Jersey as they wanted to have the cake and eat it.
So they wanted the opaqueness and maximal profit of a partnership with the protection of a separate legal entity which would be on the hook instead of the partners.
In a normal partnership, if the business decisions go sour, the partners are on the hook as their share of the partnership makes them legally responsible.
For example, if an accounting firm screws up while auditing and the audited company goes belly up, the partners of the accounting firm would be directly responsible for possible law suits by damaged share holders of stock companies.
Partnerships would ensure that the partners of the accounting firm would have skin in the game thus forcing them to be stringent.
Limited Liability Partnerships do away with such precautions and the accounting firms can happily screw up without fearing the repercussions: fees for me, losses for the public. Hurray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-of-tax-havens&quot;&gt;Advantages of Tax Havens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas the creation of the EuroMarket served the purpose of moving money into a less regulated sphere where it could generate more profits free from capital controls, the origin of tax havens is more muddled.
Ostensibly, their original purpose was the provision of low tax and preferential tax regimes, but early on they put an increased emphasis on secrecy for individuals.
Meyer Lansky had deep ties to the Bahamas and used them to launder money for the mob.
Many of the trust regulations were aimed at people hiding their wealth as much from their families as from the tax authorities.
In general, tax havens offered secrecy jurisdiction perks, of which tax evasion was a natural consequence since you can’t tax what you can’t see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multinational enterprises (MNE) are one of the financial players which use the preferential tax regimes of tax havens extensively.
When people talk about tax evasion or tax avoidance, most of the lost tax revenues is due to multinationals not paying appropriate taxes.
With the globalization of economies, many supply chains stretch across half the world.
In fact 2/3 of all trade is done within multinationals as they move products and components over their supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way multinationals cheat on governments tax revenue is through ‘transfer pricing’.
Many multinationals have subsidiaries registered in different countries which sell components to each other as products move along the supply chain.
Imagine that the iPhone is developed in a high tax country such as the US and sold by the sales department which is registered in a low tax country.
The development division can sell the iPhone for a low price to the sales department thereby making only little profit in the high tax country.
This creates a loss for the development division as R&amp;amp;D and production is expensive and they are selling the products cheaply.
The sales department then sells the iPhone for the original price but as its registered in a low tax country such as Luxembourg or Ireland, there is only little tax on its profits.
The mother company, Apple, thus pockets the difference in the tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transfer pricing has led to some astonishing price mechanisms.
Examples are water plastic seals from the Czech Republic to the parent company for 972.98 USD per unit, gloves from China for 4,121.81 USd a kilo and locks from France for 3,067.17 per Kilo.
These import prices made the parent companies in the US overpay such that parent company reduced its profits on which it could be taxed.
Exports from the US were stupendously low as missiles exported to Israel were priced at 52.03 USD a piece, diamonds were exported to India at 13.45 USD carat, cameras were suddenly worth 7.44 USD when exported to Colombia and car seats were exported for a mere 1.66 USD to Belgium.
So when the US parent company sold something, these were priced very low as it crossed the border to a subsidiary in another country.
The parent company in the US made little profit which incurred little absolute taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google for example sold the IP of its search engine algorithm to an Irish subsidiary to which it pays licensing fees.
The fees are costs for the US operations, thus diminishing the corporate tax rate, and profits for the low tax Irish subsidiary.
Similar schemes have led Ireland have trade surplus of 25% of its GDP which grossly distorts macro economic numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect is the complete disregard for prudent finance and financial safeguards in offshore financial centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe for offshore financial centers, every country has capital requirements for banks.
These capital requirements stipulate that a bank or financial institution has to keep a certain percentage of its assets as cash such that if the assets go bad, the financial corporation can offset the loss immediately with the cash reserves and is not endangered by the sudden loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these cash requirements are understandably cumbersome for the financial companies as it is money they can’t put to use to generate profits.
Offshore financial centers are attractive insofar as they reduce financial prudence to a minimum and require very little capital requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes interesting once we look at how credit increases the money supply.
Most money is actually not printed by the central banks but generated through credit.
A bank never actually has all the money of all the depositors on hand at all times but only has a little amount at its immediate disposal to fulfill the withdrawals of customers.
Most of the money is tied up in long term loans and only because only a few customers withdraw all their money at once allows the bank to keep functioning with only little cash at hand.
If all customers would withdraw their money all at once, due to a loss of faith in the bank safekeeping their wealth, we would have a bank run and the bank wouldn’t be able to pay out all its depositors and panic would ensue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets assume that we have 100 USD, and the capital requirement $r$ is 10%.
This means we have to keep 10% in cash at our bank and loan out 90% to another financial player.
The second party now has 90 USD and can in turn make loans to a third party with the remaining 81 USD once the 9 USD cash is kept.
The third party now gets 81 USD and can give out 72.9 USD in a new loan after subtracting the 10% capital requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
M_1 &amp;= M_0 *(1-r) &amp;&amp;= 90 \\
M_2 &amp;= M_1 * (1-r) = 100 * (1-r)^2 &amp;&amp;= 81 \\
M_3 &amp;= M_2 * (1-r) = 100 * (1-r)^3 &amp;&amp;= 72.9 \\
M_4 &amp;= \ldots
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This forms a geometric series and if we were to continue to infinity, we’d get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
M_\infty = \sum_k^\infty M_0 \cdot (1-r)^k = \frac{M_0}{r}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With $r=10% we increase the money supply tenfold but more importantly we create a chain of dependencies in terms of credit.
By reducing the capital requirements we make every financial institution more susceptible to defaults, the chain along which the money bounces through the system longer and ultimately the entire system more fragile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offshore finance centres are appealing to the financial system as transactions are done in almost complete darkness due to the lack of oversight.
Additionally, extremely restrained regulation basically results in little financial prudence i.e. very low capital requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in a ballooning amount of EuroDollars created in this offshore market and an almost impenetrable interdependence between financial institutions.
It is thus no wonder that the offshore markets were a great amplifier, conduit and source of the financial crises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem in offshore financial markets is the proliferation of special purpose vehicles that are created by their parent companies.
The sole purpose of these subsidiary legal entities is to separate the risk of ventures in the SPV from the parent company.
The assets do not appear on the balance sheet of the parent company and SPV’s have their own assets, liabilities and financial statements, yet the business decisions are made by the parent company.
Upon creation, the rules and purpose of these vehicles are clearly defined and it receives funding from investors to buy the agreed-upon assets in its creation document.
The lendors to the SPV can buy bonds or shares of the SPV and the worth of the SPV is defined by the assets it bought from the raised funds.
Mostly SPVs are used for securitization, such that interest payments far into the future can be monetized into lump sum that the originator of the security can book now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enron used special purpose vehicles (SPV) in the Bahamas to offload debt.
They sold their debt to specifically designed SPV’s, such that their debt was offloaded into the Caribbean ocean.
Since their financial statements were separate from Enron itself, the parent company in Houston could claim to be superb financial health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Northern Rock used the Granite SPV to offload mortgages into the offshore world and clean its balance sheet.
The Granite SPV eventually grew to 50 billion USD but was hidden from regulators as the position did not occur on the balance sheet.
The creation of SPVs in offshore financial markets is so popular due to their laxer regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the reason why the Bahamas claim to have 75% of the worlds hedge funds incorporated within their jurisdiction.
Long-Term Capital Management for example was incorporated in the Bahamas and executed their massively leveraged investment strategy from there.
AIG Financial Products that almost tanked the insurance giant all on its own by selling Credit Default Swaps to everybody asking was located in the City of London.
These are just a few examples in which the non-existent regulation of offshore financial markets have resulted in massive collateral damage to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-for-tax-havens&quot;&gt;Advantages for Tax Havens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax havens themselves earn little through taxes as they have reduced them to basically zero or at least to a miniscule rate.
Instead they use indirect taxation through the paying of fees and the support of a specialized work force which they can tax more.
In bona-fide tax havens which specialize in company, trust and foundation registration, yearly fees are required which make up for the lost revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that tax havens often sell out their sovereignty at the expense of their own citizens.
Many of them levy taxes on their citizens, while non-residents and their financial products are exempt from almost all to all taxes.
Instead, they make money by taxing the lawyers, accountants and other financial services professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, this is exactly a problem as tax havens rely disproportionally on a single industry which makes them increasingly susceptible to sudden changes in regulatory framework of other countries.
The poverty rate of Luxembourg has increased twofold as any redistributional policies are prevented on purpose.
The spoils of the offshore financial services industry thus accrues in the hands of a small and often non-resident work force while the main population suffers from the cuts in basic services and increasing house prices and costs of living.
The crown dependency of Jersey is another example where the local population is suffering disproportionately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The small size of most tax havens gives the local governments little to work with.
Would you build a huge production plant in a country with a demand of just 500.000 people?
In case of the Bahamas, the only thing they have beyond offshore financial services is sugar which is hardly a future proof or otherwise lucrative source of income for the country.
The small size also increases the probability that the country is ruled by an oligarchic or plutocratic elite which can utilize the proposed deregulation and offshoring as they make the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, offshore finance requires little capital as you only need a good internet or phone connection and a postbox which can be claimed as a headquarter by 2.000 to 12.000 offshore companies.
Give or take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ### How to Combat Offshore Finance

HW p.92: Global Financial Registry

apportion taxes proportional to payroll, sales

## Globalized Finance

from 1950 to 1975 unusual long prosperity 4 to 4.6% (Glorieux Trenteuse in France) despite high tax rate TI77

2006 lower hourly wage of worker after inflation than 1970

1973 to 2000: 17 banking crises and 57 currency crises vs 16 before

US deregulation 1974 [?] --&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="otherblog" /><summary type="html">Drinking a Pina Colada and getting wet[&amp;rich] in the rain</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RSA Cryptography: The Math</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/RSA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RSA Cryptography: &lt;br&gt; The Math" /><published>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/RSA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/RSA/">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.MathJax_Display, .MJXc-display, .MathJax_SVG_Display {
    overflow-x: auto;
    overflow-y: hidden;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt; MathJax.Hub.Config({ TeX: { equationNumbers: { autoNumber: &quot;all&quot; } } }); &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt;
         MathJax.Hub.Config({
           tex2jax: {
             inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], [&quot;\\(&quot;,&quot;\\)&quot;] ],
             processEscapes: true,
           },
		   TeX: {extensions:[&quot;autoload-all.js&quot;]}
         });
       &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-advantages-of-public-private-key-encryption&quot;&gt;The advantages of public private key encryption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all used to having access to secure communication that we seldomly ask ourselves how the encryption that keeps prying eyes from reading our messages actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is in fact the best way to &lt;strong&gt;establish&lt;/strong&gt; secure communications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most secret agent movies, there exists a cypher which allows the hero, or the villain, to decode a hidden or encrypted text into its original meaning.
Either it’s selecting specific letters from the newspaper or it’s running a tremendously exciting looking algorithm over some text files on a computer.
But in both cases the hero, or the villain, is already in possession of the knowledge how to decrypt the encrypted text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how did he obtain it knowledge to decrypt the encrypted text?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, it’s very dangerous to simply send the decryption key, whatever form it may take, through the plain mail.
It could get intercepted and copied, rendering any further encrypted communication worthless, as the copied decryption key allows the interceptor to decrypt of the secret message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in asymmetric cryptography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best analogy that I can think of is, that the person who wants to receive encrypted messages passes out publicly an abundance of &lt;strong&gt;open&lt;/strong&gt; locks to which only he has the key to unlock them.
So another person who wants to send you encrypted messages can simply pick up a publicly available open lock, but the message inside, lock it and send you the message.
Since only you have the key to all of these locks, you’re the only one who can open the lock and actually look at what you were sent.
If you were to reply, you would simply pick up a lock that the other persons has publicly on offer, lock you message up and send him or her your message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept is nice in theory, but how would it work technically and provable mathematically?
Let us establish some basics first which will be important down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modulo-the-secret-sauce-of-rsa-imho&quot;&gt;Modulo: The Secret Sauce of RSA IMHO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modulo operator $x \ mod \ n$ takes any number $x$ and returns the remainder after the division with $n$.
Let’s say you want to know $x \ mod \ n$, then we can represent $x$ as $x= k n + r$ for an integer $k$ and the remainder $r$.
The modulo operator is in fact not very complicated and it should be clear after a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{aligned}
  x \mod \ n &amp;= r \quad \text{since}  \quad &amp;&amp;  x = k * n + r    &amp;&amp; \quad \text{with} \quad k \in \mathbb{N}, r \in \mathbb{N} \\ \\
  9 \mod \ 2 &amp;= 1 \quad \text{since}  \quad &amp;&amp;  9 = 4 * 2 + 1    &amp;&amp; \quad \text{with} \quad k=4, r=1 \\
  13 \mod \ 2 &amp;= 1 \quad \text{since} \quad &amp;&amp; 13 = 6 * 2 + 1    &amp;&amp; \quad \text{with} \quad k=6, r=1 \\ \\
  5 \mod \ 3 &amp;= 2 \quad \text{since}  \quad &amp;&amp; 5  = 1 * 3 + 2    &amp;&amp; \quad \text{with} \quad k=1, r=2 \\
  8 \mod \ 3 &amp;= 2 \quad \text{since}  \quad &amp;&amp; 8  = 2 * 3 + 2    &amp;&amp; \quad \text{with} \quad k=2, r=2 \\
\end{aligned} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the examples with care to highlight a natural property of the modulo operator which makes it so appealing to cryptography.
Namely, that we apply the modulo operator on different numbers and will obtain the same remainder.
If you’re only left with the number $n$ and the remainder $r$, there is no way to obtain the original number $x$.
The modulo operator is basically a one way operation which hides the original number $x$!
The properties of the modulo function that will be important to us only consider large integer values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coprime-integers&quot;&gt;Coprime Integers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next ingredient that is required are coprime integers.
‘Coprime’ might sound threatening and complicated but in fact the definition is quite simple.
Two integer numbers are coprime if their greatest common divisor is 1, $\text{gcd}(a, b)=1$ for $a, b \in \mathbb{N}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In laymen’s terms, this means that both numbers are divisible into an integer only by the number of one.
So for example, 3 and 5 are coprime because 1 is the largest integer divisor of both of them.
The numbers 3 and 15 and not coprime because the greatest common denominator is 3.
The latter example is still divisible by 1 as well, but we’re talking about the &lt;em&gt;greatest&lt;/em&gt; common divisor of two integer numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eulers-totient&quot;&gt;Eulers Totient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For $n \in \mathbb{N}$, Euler’s totient is given as the number of integer numbers $m$ that are in the set&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
\phi(n) = \{m \in \mathbb{N} \ | \ 1 \leq m \leq n, \text{gcd}(m, n) = 1 \}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which essentially means that we want the number of integers that are smaller than $n$ and are coprime to $n$.
As an example let’s look at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi(9) = | \{1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 8 \} |  = 6&lt;/script&gt;.
The numbers 3, 6 and 9 are not members of $\phi(9)$ because their greatest common divisor is 3, so the restriction $\text{gcd}(\{ 3,6,9 \}, 9) =1$ does not hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly for our application, Euler’s totient is a multiplicative function for two numbers which are relatively prime, or coprime, to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
  \phi(n) = \phi(pq) = \phi(p) \phi(q) \quad ; \text{gcd}(p, q)=1
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, taking Euler’s totient of a prime number $p \in \mathbb{P}$ returns $\phi(p) = p-1$ since a prime number is only divisible by 1 or itself and thus every number before $p$ falls into the category of Euler’s totient. This will be important later for the RSA algorithm …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eulers-theorem-the-bedrock-of-rsa&quot;&gt;Eulers Theorem: The Bedrock of RSA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impressive Leonhard Euler ( I mean come on, the guy lived 250 years ago and so much of our modern technological applications are based on his math) found out that if $n$ and $a$ are coprime, the following identity holds:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\left[ a^{\phi(n)} = 1 \right] \mod \ n.&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notation $[ \ldots ] \mod n$ means that we apply the modulo equally to both sides. The notation $\ldots = \ldots (\mod n)$ is more common but I like my paranthesis to clearly delineate what operator we apply to what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it turns out that we can massage Euler’s Theorem into a very useful form, namely
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
  \Big[ a^{\phi(n)}       &amp;= 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
  \Big[ a^{k\phi(n)}      &amp;= 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right here we smuggled in the integer number $k$ in the exponentiation.
In order to prove the validity of this step, we can construct the following ‘proof’ (Hey, I ain’t no mathematician, but at least the math checks out),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
  \Big[ a^{k\phi(n)}      = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
  \Big[ {\big( a^{\phi(n)} \big) }^k      = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
  \Big[ \prod_i^k {\big( a^{\phi(n)} \big) }      = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
for which we can now employ the transitivity rule which states that
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
  &amp; \Big[ ab \Big] \mod n \\
  =&amp; \Big[ [a] \ \text{mod} \ n \cdot [b] \ \text{mod} \ n \Big] \mod n \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which gives us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
  \Big[ \prod_i^k {\big( a^{\phi(n)} \big) }      = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
  \Bigg[ \prod_i^k \Big( \Big[ \underbrace{a^{\phi(n)} \Big] \ \text{mod} \ n}_{=1} \Big)      = 1 \Bigg] \mod \ n \\
  \Bigg[ \prod_i^k \Big( 1 \Big)      = 1 \Bigg] \mod \ n \\
  \Bigg[  1   = 1 \Bigg] \mod \ n.
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which proves that we can add an integer multiplier in the exponent.
Carrying on we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
  &amp; \Big[ a^{\phi(n)}       = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \\
  &amp; \Big[ a^{k\phi(n)}      = 1 \Big] \mod \ n \quad \Big| \cdot a \\
  &amp; \Big[ a^{k \phi(n)+ 1}  = a \Big] \mod \ n \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation above tells us that for some integer number $k$ about which we don’t really care and the number $n$ we can exponentiate the number $a$ with $k \phi(n)+1$ and under the $\text{mod} \ n$ regime we will obtain the same number $a$.
The cool thing that Euler’s Theorem allows us to do is that we can obviously factorize, respectively construct, the exponent $k \phi(n)+1$ in any way we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is where we finally get to the main RSA algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rsa-encryption&quot;&gt;RSA Encryption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rivest-Shamir-Adleman cryptosystem leans heavily, and almost exclusively, on Euler’s theorem to enable an asymmetric cryptographic system.
It starts out by taking a message, which are just numbers for computers, and exponentiating it with the secret key $e$ and applying the modulo operator $\text{mod} \ n $ to it to generate an encrypted cypher text $c$,
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
\text{Encryption}: \quad c = [ x^e ] \mod n.
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can conclude that we only need the encryption key $e$ (which is a number) and the modulo basis $n$ (which is also just a number) to be public to enable anybody to encrypt a message for us.
The almost identical operation, albeit with the secret key $d$, is performed to decrypt the cypher message $c$,
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
\text{Decryption}: \quad x = [ c^d ] \mod n
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is obviously whether there is a strict one-to-one correspondence between the encryption and the decryption.
Because a cryptographic system which maps multiple messages into the same decrypted message is absolutely worthless.
To show this, we can again employ Euler’s theorem to guarantee the needed one-to-one correspondence, such that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
[ c^d &amp;= x ] \mod n \\
\Big[ \big( [ x^e ] \mod n \big)^d &amp;= x \Big] \mod n \\
\Big[ \prod^d_i \big( [ x^e ] \mod n \big) &amp;= x \Big] \mod n \quad \\
\Big[ \prod^d_i x^e &amp;= x \Big] \mod n \quad \text{(Transitivity Rule)} \\
\Big[ \big( x^e \big)^d &amp;= x \Big] \mod n \\
\Big[ x^{ed} &amp;= x \Big] \mod n \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus if we are able to find a corresponding exponent in our encryption/decryption scheme that fulfills Euler’s theorem, we have a wonderful asymmetric cryptographic system which checkmarks all the requirements we wanted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
\Big[ x^{ed} &amp;= x \Big] \mod \ n \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad \Big[ a^{k \phi(n)+ 1}  = a \Big] \mod \ n 
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of the modulo operator is that it’s really hard to guess the correct $d$ since there are an infinite number of possible $d$’s due to the arbitrary $k$ for which the modulo operator returns a possible correct $x$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only remaining question is now how to choose the modulo basis $n$ of which we want to compute Euler’s totient &lt;strong&gt;efficiently&lt;/strong&gt;. 
Naturally, we want $n$ to be very large such that an interceptor can’t simply try out all the $k$’s and Euler’s totient $\phi(n)$’s by brute force, since the RSA key generation scheme for $e$ and $d$ is public.
Instead we want a very, very large number $n$ for which it is almost impossible to determine the totient $\phi(n)$ by brute force, but which we construct in such a way that we know the totient in single evaluation during the key generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this we will use the previousuly stated property of the totient that if two numbers are coprime to each other, we can simply factorize the totient into the multiplicative components.
Furthermore we can leverage the fact, and this is extremely important for the RSA cryptographic system, that Euler’s totient of a prime number $p$ is just $\phi(p)= p-1$ since a prime number is integer divisible only by itself and one.
This means that Euler’s totient for prime numbers is just the respective prime number reduced by one, which means that every number before the prime number is coprime to it as the greatest common divisor of a prime number is 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus if we construct $n=pq$ from two very large, but distinct, prime numbers $p, q \in \mathbb{P}$, we can factorize the practically incalculable totient of $n$ into a fairly easily computable product,
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
\phi(n) = \phi(p)\phi(q) = (p-1)(q-1).
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that the main effort of the RSA cryptographic system lies with the generation of two very large prime numbers which have to remain secret as they are used during the generation of the private key.
Just to reiterate, computing Euler’s totient $\phi(n)$ for a very large $n$ is practically impossible at the moment (but let’s maybe wait for quantum computers), while the private knowledge of the two prime numbers $p$ and $q$ which constitute $n$ multiplicatively allows us to generate a correct private key quite easily.
In fact after having generated $p$ and $q$ we can simply pick a super large $k$ and determine $d$ quite easily as $d=(k(p-1)(q-1)+1)/e$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get the mathematical equivalency that the encryption and subsequent decryption under the modulo $n$ operation is valid, all we have to do is find a $d$ for which holds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
e d &amp;= k \phi(n)+1 \\
e d &amp;= k \phi(pq)+1 \\
e d &amp;= k \phi(p) \phi(q) + 1 \\
e d &amp;= k (p-1)(q-1) + 1 \\
\Big[ ed &amp;= 1 \Big] \mod (p-1)(q-1) \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which tells us that we are indeed generating the private key $d$ with the private ingredients of $\phi(p)$ and $\phi(q)$
of our two secret prime numbers $p$ and $q$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing to check is that $a$ and $n$ are indeed coprime (not necessarily prime themselves) which happens with overwhelming probability as $n$ becomes increasingly large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;signatures-in-rsa&quot;&gt;Signatures in RSA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intriguing property of the public private key encryption is its ability to sign messages as a sender through the use of a cryptographic hash function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cryptographic hash maps data of an arbitrary size to a bit array of fixed size.
It is by all practical means a seemingly random function, although it is in fact deterministic but people have spent a lot of time perfecting the ostensible randomness.
Importantly, hash functions should be quick to compute, infeasible to reverse and to find two messages with the same hash and finally changing the input message slightly should return a completely different hash.
Illustratively, hash functions permute input, cycle over it a couple of times and do all other crazy things to map the variable input length array into a fixed one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s get back to RSA …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sender would send the message through a hash function $h = hash(x)$ and subsequently exponentiate it with the private key $d$.
The receiver can then exponetiate the ‘decrypted’ hash again with the public key $e$ and take the modulo of it and compare it to his or her own hash of the sent message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically, we can employ Euler’s theorem again, having defined the product of the private and public key as $ed = k \phi(n)+1$, to obtain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
  \Big[ {\big(h^d \big)}^e &amp;= h \Big] \mod n \\
  \Big[  h^{de} &amp;= h \Big] \mod n \quad ed = k\phi(n)+1 \\
  \Big[  h^{k\phi(n)+1} &amp;= h \Big] \mod n \quad \text{True via Euler's theorem} \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cha-Ching Baby …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The math that ensures that it's none of your business</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Berlin Over The Years</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Berlin Over The Years" /><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Berlin2021/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-1.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-1&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-13&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-13.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-13&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-13&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-13.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-13.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-15.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-15&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-15.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-15&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-15&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-15.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-15.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-170.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-170&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-170.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-170&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-170&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-170&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-170.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-170.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-180.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-180&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-180.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-180&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-180&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-180&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-180.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-180.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-190.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-190&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-190.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-190&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-190&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-190&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-190.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-190.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-201.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-201&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-201.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-201&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-201&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-201&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-201.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-201.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-61.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-61&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-61.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;Berlin-61&quot; title=&quot;Berlin-61&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berlin-61&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-61.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-61.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4686.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC4686&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4686.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC4686&quot; title=&quot;DSC4686&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC4686&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4686.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4686.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4952.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC4952&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4952.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC4952&quot; title=&quot;DSC4952&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC4952&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4952.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/berlin2021/DSC4952.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/berlin2021/Berlin-15.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Spain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Spain21/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spain" /><published>2021-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Spain21</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Spain21/">&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2100.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2100&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2100.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2100&quot; title=&quot;DSC2100&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2100.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2100.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2101.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2101&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2101.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2101&quot; title=&quot;DSC2101&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2101&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2101.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2101.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2102&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2102&quot; title=&quot;DSC2102&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2102&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102_.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2102_&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102_.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2102_&quot; title=&quot;DSC2102_&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2102_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102_.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2102_.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2103.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2103&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2103.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2103&quot; title=&quot;DSC2103&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2103&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2103.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2103.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2260.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2260&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2260.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2260&quot; title=&quot;DSC2260&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2260&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2260.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2260.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2439.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2439&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2439.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2439&quot; title=&quot;DSC2439&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2439&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2439.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2439.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2453.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2453&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2453.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2453&quot; title=&quot;DSC2453&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2453&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2453.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2453.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2492.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2492&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2492.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2492&quot; title=&quot;DSC2492&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2492&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2492.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2492.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2748.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2748&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2748.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2748&quot; title=&quot;DSC2748&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2748&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2748.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2748.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">Granada</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/spain21/DSC2103.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Greece</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Greece21/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greece" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Greece21</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Greece21/">&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1780.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1780&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1780.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1780&quot; title=&quot;DSC1780&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1780&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1780.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1780.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1783.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1783&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1783.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1783&quot; title=&quot;DSC1783&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1783&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1783.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1783.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1784.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1784&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1784.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1784&quot; title=&quot;DSC1784&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1784&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1784.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1784.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1888.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1888&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1888.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1888&quot; title=&quot;DSC1888&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1888&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1888.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1888.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1918.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1918&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1918.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1918&quot; title=&quot;DSC1918&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1918&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1918.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1918.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1924.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1924&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1924.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1924&quot; title=&quot;DSC1924&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1924&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1924.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1924.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2009.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2009&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2009.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2009&quot; title=&quot;DSC2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2009&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2009.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2009.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2023.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2023&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2023.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2023&quot; title=&quot;DSC2023&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2023.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2023.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2127.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC2127&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2127.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC2127&quot; title=&quot;DSC2127&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC2127&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2127.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC2127.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">Thessaloniki &amp; Mount Olympus</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/greece21/DSC1783.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Italy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Italy21/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Italy" /><published>2021-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Italy21</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Italy21/">&lt;!-- ## Berlin Over The Years --&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .image-gallery {overflow: auto; margin-left: -1%!important;}
    .image-gallery li {float: left; float: top; display: block; margin: 0 0 1% 1%; width: 99%;}
    .image-gallery li a {text-align: top; text-decoration: none!important; color: #777;}
    .image-gallery li a span {display: block; text-overflow: ellipsis; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; padding: 3px 0;}
    .image-gallery li a img {width: 100%; height: 100%; display: flex; vertical-align: top;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;image-gallery&quot;&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0927.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC0927&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0927.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC0927&quot; title=&quot;DSC0927&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC0927&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0927.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0927.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0939.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC0939&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0939.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC0939&quot; title=&quot;DSC0939&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC0939&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0939.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0939.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0940.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC0940&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0940.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC0940&quot; title=&quot;DSC0940&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC0940&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0940.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0940.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0950.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC0950&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0950.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC0950&quot; title=&quot;DSC0950&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC0950&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0950.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0950.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0966.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC0966&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0966.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC0966&quot; title=&quot;DSC0966&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC0966&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0966.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0966.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1065.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1065&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1065.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1065&quot; title=&quot;DSC1065&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1065&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1065.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1065.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1169.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1169&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1169.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1169&quot; title=&quot;DSC1169&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1169&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1169.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1169.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1181.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1181&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1181.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1181&quot; title=&quot;DSC1181&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1181&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1181.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1181.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1447.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1447&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1447.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1447&quot; title=&quot;DSC1447&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1447&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1447.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1447.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1614.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1614&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1614.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1614&quot; title=&quot;DSC1614&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1614&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1614.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1614.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1719.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1719&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1719.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1719&quot; title=&quot;DSC1719&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1719&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1719.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1719.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    &lt;!-- &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1722-Pano.jpg&quot; title=&quot;DSC1722-Pano&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//images.weserv.nl/?url=localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1722-Pano.jpg&amp;w=300&amp;h=300&amp;output=jpg&amp;q=50&amp;t=square&quot; alt=&quot;DSC1722-Pano&quot; title=&quot;DSC1722-Pano&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt;DSC1722-Pano&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1722-Pano.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC1722-Pano.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography" /><summary type="html">Lake Garda, Milan, Bergamo, Brescia</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/photo_gallery/italy21/DSC0940.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Reverse Time Stochastic Differential Equations [for generative modelling]</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/ReverseTimeAnderson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reverse Time Stochastic Differential Equations [for generative modelling]" /><published>2021-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/ReverseTimeAnderson</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/ReverseTimeAnderson/">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.MathJax_Display, .MJXc-display, .MathJax_SVG_Display {
    overflow-x: auto;
    overflow-y: hidden;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt; MathJax.Hub.Config({ TeX: { equationNumbers: { autoNumber: &quot;all&quot; } } }); &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script type=&quot;text/x-mathjax-config&quot;&gt;
         MathJax.Hub.Config({
           tex2jax: {
             inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], [&quot;\\(&quot;,&quot;\\)&quot;] ],
             processEscapes: true
           },
		   TeX: {extensions:[&quot;autoload-all.js&quot;]}
         });
       &lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is a derivation of the main result of ‘Reverse-Time Diffusion Equation Models’ by Brian D.O. Anderson (1982).
Earlier on this blog we learned that a stochastic differential equation of the form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
	dX_t = \mu(X_t, t) dt + \sigma(X_t, t) dW_t
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with the derivative of Wiener process $W_t$ admits two types of equations, called the forward Kolmogorov or Fokker-Planck equation and the backward Kolmogorov equation.
For notational brevity we will use the term $\mu(x_t)$ for the drift and $\sigma(x_t)$ as the diffusion parameter and omit the explicit time dependency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kolmogorov forward equation is identical to the Fokker Planck equation and states&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
	\partial_t p(x_t) = -\partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) p(x_t) \right] + \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right].
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It describes the evolution of a probability distribution $p(x_t)$ forward in time.
We can quite frankly think of it as, for example, a Normal distribution being slowly transformed into an arbitrary complex distribution according to the drift and diffusion parameters $\mu(x_t)$ and $\sigma(x_t)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kolmogorov backward equation for $t \leq s$ is defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
	- \partial_t p(x_s | x_t) = \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_s|x_t) + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t)
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it basically answers the question how the probability of $x_s$ at a later point in time changes as we change $x_t$ at an earlier point in time.
The Kolmogorov backward equation is somewhat confounding with respect to time as we’re taking the partial derivative with respect to the earlier time step $t$ on which we are also coniditoning.
But we can think of it as asking ‘How does the probability of $x_s$ at the later point in time $s$ change, as we slowly evolve the probability distribution backwards through time and condition on $x_t$’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking inspiration from our crude example earlier, the backward equation offers a partial differential equation which we can solve backward in time, which would correspond to evolving the arbitrarily complex distribution backwards to our original Normal distribution. 
Unfortunately there is no corresponding stochastic differential equation with a drift and diffusion term that describes the evolution of a random variable backwards through time in terms of a stochastic differential equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the remarkable result from Anderson (1982) comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The granddaddy of all probabilistic equations, Bayes theorem, tells us that a joint distribution can be factorized by conditioning: $p(x_s , x_t) = p(x_s|x_t) p(x_t)$ with the time ordering $t \leq s$.
Why do we invoke the joint probability $p(x_s, x_t)$ we might ask?
What we’re trying to achieve is to derive a stochastic differential equation that tells us from what values of $x_t$ we can arrive at $x_s$.
We can ask ourselves what the partial differential equation would be that describes the evolution of the joint distribution over time.
First multiplying both sides of Bayes theorem with minus one and taking the derivative with respect to time $t$, we obtain via the product rule&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	- \partial_t p(x_s, x_t) &amp;= - \partial_t \left[ p(x_s| x_t) p(x_t) \right] \\
	&amp;= \underbrace{-\partial_t p(x_s|x_t)}_{\text{KBE}} p(x_t) - p(x_s | x_t) \underbrace{\partial_t p(x_t)}_{\text{KFE}}
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;into which we can plug in the Kolmogorov forward (KFE) and Kolmogorov backward (KBE) equations,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	&amp; -\partial_t p(x_s|x_t) p(x_t) - p(x_s | x_t) \partial_t p(x_t) \\
	&amp;= \left( \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_s|x_t) + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \right) p(x_t) \\
	&amp; + p(x_s| x_t) \left( \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) p(x_t) \right] - \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right)
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The derivative occuring in the backward Kolmogorov equation are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	\partial_{x_t} p(x_s|x_t) &amp;= \partial_{x_t} \left[ \frac{p(x_s, x_t)}{p(x_t)} \right] \\
	&amp; = \frac{\partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t) p(x_t) - p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)}{p^2(x_t)} \\
	&amp; = \frac{\partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t)}{p(x_t)} - \frac{p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)}{p^2(x_t)}
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to evaluate the derivative of the products in the forward Kolmogorov equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	\partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) p(x_t) \right] &amp; = \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t) \ p(x_t) + \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t) \\
	\partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] &amp; = \partial_{x_t}^2 \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) + 2 \ \partial_{x_t} \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t) + \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_t)
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging in the derivatives of the probability distributions we obtain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	- \partial_t p(x_s, x_t)
	= &amp; - \partial_t \left[ p(x_s| x_t) p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; -\partial_t p(x_s|x_t) p(x_t) - p(x_s | x_t) \partial_t p(x_t) \\
	= &amp; \left( \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_s|x_t) + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \right) p(x_t) \\
	&amp; + p(x_s| x_t) \left( \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) p(x_t) \right] - \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right) \\
	= &amp; \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_s|x_t) \ p(x_t) 
	+ \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) \\
	&amp; + p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t) \ p(x_t) + p(x_s| x_t) \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t) \\
	&amp; - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \mu(x_t) \ \left(\frac{\partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t)}{\cancel{p(x_t)}} - \frac{p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)}{p^{\cancel{2}}(x_t)} \right) \ \cancel{p(x_t)} \\
	&amp; + p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t) \ p(x_t) + p(x_s| x_t) \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t) \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \mu(x_t) \ \left(\partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t) - \frac{p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)}{p(x_t)} \right) \\
	&amp; + p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t) \ p(x_t) + p(x_s| x_t) \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t) \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \mu(x_t) \ \left(\partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t) - \cancel{p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)} \right) \\
	&amp; + p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t) + \cancel{p(x_s| x_t) \mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_t)} \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \underbrace{\mu(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t} p(x_s, x_t) + p(x_s, x_t) \partial_{x_t} \mu(x_t)}_{\text{product rule}} \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right]
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now see that the drift term already fulfills the requirements of the forward Kolmogorov equation.
What we’re left with and which we have to take care of are the two terms with the diffusion terms $\sigma^2(x_t)$.
The goal is to fuse the two terms into one which resembles the diffusion term in the forward Kolmogorov equation.
Just to reiterate it one more time, if we can massage the partial differential equation into the functional form of the Kolmogorov forward equation, we have a one-to-one correspondence to a stochastic differential equation that can be solved backward in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the gracious help from Brian Anderson himself in an email from down under, we can simplify the terms with $\sigma^2(x_t)$ by expanding the last term.
The important step, that Brian pointed out to me, is to factorize the joint distribution $p(x_s, x_t) = p(x_s| x_t) p(x_t)$ and invoke the product rule to match the terms,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	&amp; \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p(x_s, x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p(x_s | x_t) p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) + \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \partial_{x_t} p(x_s| x_t)
	 + \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] p(x_s| x_t)
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see from the expansion of the derivative above that we can combine the terms in our derivation if we expand the “center term”.
Furthermore we can employ the identity $-\frac{1}{2} X = -X + \frac{1}{2} X$ to obtain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
	-\partial_t p(x_s, x_t)
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t) - \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) - \underbrace{ \frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] }_{-\frac{1}{2} X = -X + \frac{1}{2} X} \\
	&amp; \pm \partial_{x_t} p(x_s | x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] \\
	&amp; \textcolor{red}{+ \frac{1}{2} \ \sigma^2(x_t) \ \partial_{x_t}^2 p(x_s | x_t) \ p(x_t)} \\
	&amp; \underbrace{ - p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] + \textcolor{red}{\frac{1}{2} p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right]} }_{-\frac{1}{2} X = -X + \frac{1}{2} X} \\
	&amp; \textcolor{red}{\pm \partial_{x_t} p(x_s | x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right]} \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] + \textcolor{red}{\frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p( x_s | x_t) p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right]} \\
	&amp; \underbrace{- p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] - \partial_{x_t} p(x_s | x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right]}_{
		- \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right] \text{ (product rule) }
		} \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) \right] + \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p( x_s , x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \\
	&amp; - \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right] \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ \mu(x_t) \ p(x_s, x_t) - p(x_s| x_t) \partial_{x_t} \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right] \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p( x_s , x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right] \\
	= &amp; \partial_{x_t} \left[ p(x_s, x_t) \left( \mu(x_t) - \frac{1}{p(x_t)} \partial_{x_t} \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right) \right] \\
	&amp; + \frac{1}{2} \partial_{x_t}^2 \left[ p( x_s , x_t) \sigma^2(x_t) \right]
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which finally gives us a stochastic differential equation that we can solve backward in time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{align}
d\tilde{X}_t = \left(\mu(x_t) - \frac{1}{p(x_t)} \partial_{x_t} \left[ \sigma^2(x_t) \ p(x_t) \right] \right) dt + \sigma(x_t) d\tilde{W}_t
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
where $\tilde{W}_t$ is a Wiener process that flows backward in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common application of the reverse time stochastic differential equations is in generative modelling.
In these applications the noise $\sigma(x_t)$ is made independent of the input such that we can pull it out of the partial derivative $\partial_{x_t}$.
By additionally using the log-derivative trick we obtain a term which is dependent on the score&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
d\tilde{X}_t &amp;= \left(\mu(x_t) - \sigma_t^2 \frac{1}{p(x_t)} \partial_{x_t} \ p(x_t) \right) dt + \sigma_t d\tilde{W}_t \\
&amp;= \Big(\mu(x_t) - \sigma_t^2 \underbrace{\partial_{x_t} \log p(x_t)}_{\text{ML Model}} \Big) dt + \sigma_t d\tilde{W}_t \\
\end{align} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score based generative modelling proceeds by defining a, what I creatively call, ‘noising’ process which takes data and turns it into garbage by iteratively adding noise along an analytically known SDE.
The data dependent drift $\mu(x_t) = \alpha_t x_0$ with $\alpha_s &amp;gt; \alpha_t, s&amp;lt;t$ and the data independent diffusion $\sigma_t$ with $\sigma_s &amp;lt; \sigma_t, s&amp;lt; t$ are known beforehand.
In essence, the drift reduces the data $x_0$ slowly to zero while we heap more and noise on the data via the diffusion term.
More importantly, by defining an analytical SDE we can ‘jump’ to any point in time and evaluate how noisy the data $x_t$ has become without having to solve SDE explicitely.
By defining a schedule for both $\alpha_t$ and $\sigma_t$ we can evaluate the ‘noisiness’ sort of point-wise in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarkable reverse time stochastic differential equation then tells us that all we have to do is to cancel out the drift which turns our data into noise.
If we now take some noise and iteratively subtract the $\sigma_t^2 \partial_{x_t} \log p(x_t)$ from it we are reducing integration step by integration step (remember it’s a SDE) the noise and recover the true data.
Voila, you have generative model that turns noise into data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">'If I Could Turn Back Time' by Cher (1989)</summary></entry></feed>